The White House signed the super
intelligence accord. Nearly 20 tech
leaders joined the [music] president and
speaker Mike Johnson for lunch in the
East Room.
>> Great that everybody signed, but who can
tell them no? What happens if somebody
breaks the agreement?
>> There are really sort of [music] two
polls that one can worry about. One is
overregulation and then the other is
Elon laid out his case for abundance. So
technology takes whatever was scarce and
makes it abundant. That's the basic
thesis. When the essentials of a good
life become affordable and accessible,
then you have abundance.
>> Broad market exposure becomes [music]
arguably the easiest path for an entire
generation to universal high income.
Anthropic has officially filed its S1
[music] to go public. The target
valuation for the IPO is 2 trillion.
>> I think that Anthropic right now is a
fantastic business. I think they get
smashed in 2 years. I'm not even sure
Anthropic needs high temperature
superconductors in order to scale their
revenue. I think they'll have a very
bright [music] future because
>> now that's a moonshot ladies and
gentlemen.
>> This episode is brought to you by the
Abundance Summit and Link Ventures.
>> Welcome to Moonshot to everyone, your
number one podcast on all things AI and
exponential. Your front row seat to the
accelerating singularity. You know, we
just finished up the inaugural Moonshots
live event and it was awesome. It was a
blast to be physically there with all of
our listeners, 1500 people in the
audience, uh close to 100,000 people
online. Honestly, the energy in the room
was pure magic. So much outpouring of
optimism and excitement. you know,
before we, you know, jump into the
breaking news, just a a, you know, huge
thank you to everybody who attended and
everybody who watched. So, uh, Alex,
what was your favorite part of the show?
Oh, I I loved the AMA. That was just
tremendous fun. An hourish of rapid
fire, lightning mode, answering
everyone's questions, 600 people plus
packed into a relatively tiny room. It
was tremendous, tremendous fun.
>> Yeah. and and Sem, how about you pal?
>> Um, echo the Alex thing. I think if we
wanted to start a cult, we are well on
our way. The collective tissue, the
optimism in the room was really
literally religious fervor.
>> Um, you know, 2,000 people got together
and hundreds of thousand people online
imagining a positive future. We are we
might actually be able to sway the and
tilt the future. Or as Alan K said, the
best way of predicting the future is to
create it yourself. And Peter, you think
you started creating that future.
>> Yeah. And you know, one of my favorite
was one of the future vision X-P prize
uh uh writers, producers who presented
said something that is so true. He said,
you know, if you're if you're driving
and you're staring at a pothole in the
road, that's where you're going to go,
right? And so if humanity if humanity is
you know imagining and staring at at you
know p doom at 50% you know that's where
we're going to go and I think we need to
really sway the vision and optimism
right we ran the Oscars for optimism
there. How about you Immad? What was
your favorite?
>> Well yeah I love the Oscars for
optimism. uh thought the gift did as the
winner of the future vision X prize was
just immense as the result of one person
working with this amazing technology and
I can't wait for it to be turned into a
footage film.
>> We're going to show that clip. My my
favorite part was uh my AMA with with
Captain Kirk with William Shatner.
>> That was so fun. I mean I can't
>> boy was he sharp.
>> Yeah. In 95 going strong. I mean, he was
part of a what was he a rock metal band
performance a couple weeks earlier.
Insane.
>> Iron Maiden.
>> Yeah. Incredibly cool. Yeah, for sure.
>> We got to we got to we got to reverse
him a few years. You know,
>> put them on top of the list.
>> I love one of the uh one of the comments
we had from subscriber at Sublime
Delusion. He said, "Thank you, Peter."
And the Moonshot Mates Moonshot Live was
indeed the room and it was an honor to
be in it. Uh in one word, amazing. So,
uh, as always, our mission here is to
help you understand what just happened,
what it means for you, your family, your
company, and most importantly, keep you
optimistic about the abundance-minded
future that we're creating, uh, that
we're actively creating. You know, the
future is not what just happens, it's
what we make it to be. Today, we're
going to be covering seven breaking
stories that occurred in just a single
48 hour window. Everything from
America's SI leaders, I got that right,
and the entire US AI stack gathered in
DC signing a super intelligence accord
with Trump to Enthropic filing a two
trillion dollar IPO, Open AAI shipping
more than 20 products at Dev Day and
Starship reaching orbit for the first
time. As always, if you're a new
subscriber, um, thank you. If you're a
watcher and you haven't subscribed,
please do. We publish twice a week and
you don't want to miss any of these
episodes during the singularity. Uh, as
always, send us your AMA questions. We
answer those at the end and you can
follow us on uh on X at moonshots_pod.
All right, buckle up. Another amazing
week during the supersonic tsunami. So,
let's open with the biggest story of the
week and I want to take it in four
parts. Uh, first the backstory on this
roller coaster. You'll remember two
weeks ago, Dario, Sam, Elon, and Demis
all called on the industry to pace the
frontier, to slow down. Then last week,
President Trump told the reporters he
wanted to leave it exactly where it was,
that the DOJ acting as guard rails,
right? We have liability laws. We have
protections. We don't need to slow it
down. This Tuesday, Trump brought the
entire AI stack into one room. Nearly 20
tech leaders joined the president and
speaker Mike Johnson for lunch in the
East Room. Let's uh show the quick slide
here. What I found fascinating about
this uh this image of all the leaders
together at the White House is the
seating arrangement. Right there is
Trump with Jensen to one side and Elon
to the other. And then in the far left
you see Daario. I think he's been sent
to the outer pastures. Uh pretty
interesting. All right. Well, you know,
uh, Elon, Zuck, Jensen, Dario, Sundar,
Satia, Lisa Sue, and Open Eye President
Greg Brockman were there. Sam was in San
Francisco for Open Eyes Dev Day, uh,
which we'll get to in a little bit. So,
what happened? The White House signed
the Super Intelligence Accord, right, in
four layers. Let me read them out. So
layer number one, internal controls that
monitor capabilities and alignment
during training and deployment in cyber,
bio, and chemical. So models do not hack
or access technical systems in
unintended ways. Layer number two, an
internal team to make sure the controls
are actually working. Three, an external
auditor or evaluator to independently
assess them. and four, an independent
committee of each company's board of
directors to oversee it and make sure
the problems get fixed. Let me show a
quick video here of Donald Trump
speaking about this.
>> It really is a a form of protection.
They understand that they have to self
police and it's very hard for somebody
to come outside, get into these these
models are very complex and again I
believe they're going to be used for the
good and when they're not we're going to
be able to nab them. But there's going
to be a tremendous self-p policing
aspect. We're also thinking about
forming a committee of sorts where we
put maybe 10 people on that committee.
It could be from that group so that we
can so the committee can watch over the
whole enterprise.
>> Is this a core that everybody signed? Is
it binding in any way?
>> I think it's morally binding. Yeah.
>> All right. I love that. Morally binding.
Not sure what that means, but hey. So uh
I want to show a few clips from this ad
hoc press press press conference uh and
then I want to talk about the first is
Daria Amade who's standing next to the
president and he says I think this
technology has very real risks you know
he's still on that point and the
mechanisms of how we address those risks
is still under discussion. If we do this
right we work the president and everyone
here and we can win safely. So let's
take a look at Daario's commentary.
AI has incredible benefits. I've talked
about the medical benefit to the
technology. I, as the president has
said, you know, whoever wins AI wins. I
think that's very important. But I think
the technology has very real risks. And
you know, the mechanism how we address
those risks is still under discussion.
But we all need to work, we all need to
work together to make sure that we can
win and we can win safely. If we if we
do this right, if we work with the
president and everyone here, we can win
safe.
>> I wonder how many times he practiced
that line. All right, one more video and
then we'll chat about it. Next up, the
president pulls Mark Zuckerberg out of
the crowd to explain what they just
agreed to. Uh, if you remember, and we
discussed this about two weeks ago, Zuck
said he didn't think we needed
industrywide cooperation. And this week,
he's the one explaining an industry-wide
accord. But I think what we can all
agree on is that the American public and
our customers want to know that what
we're building is working in the way
that we all intend. So we drafted a set
of of principles and commitments around
building robust internal controls and
detecting if there are any issues with
the technology coupled with uh multiple
layers of of auditing and controls
starting with internal risk review,
external auditors and evaluators and
agreeing that we're going to have all of
our boards of directors independently
review the reports that come from the
auditors. I think these are good steps
forward. The idea isn't that this is the
only thing that we will ever do. It is
that this is a start and an accord that
the whole industry could come to.
>> So let's let's break this down. Alex,
>> what did you think of all of that? Is
this theor is it obvious from the video
videos that you just played and the Last
Supper image that you just displayed
who's pulling all the strings here?
Because I I think it is. So who who's
pulling all the strings? Zuck. If you
look at the last If you look at the last
supper image, I don't know if Peter you
you can display that once. I'll bring it
up again for those who are watching.
Look at the body language in that image
and and there's reporting to
substantiate this as well. But if you
look at the so-called AI last supper
image, who's the one paying close
attention to what the president is uh is
saying and doing? It's Zuck. Look, look
at Zuck in this image. He's looking to
the right. Everyone else is looking
forward. There's a little bit of Kremlin
here, AI Kremlin. And then if if you
look at if you go back to the video of
Daario speaking with uh with the
president standing behind Dario.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Can we show that one more
time? This time, don't watch Daario.
>> Watch the the dog that's not barking.
Zuck.
>> AI has incredible benefits. I've talked
about the medical benefits of the
technology.
>> Zuck is laughing, joking with the
president. Watch Zuck, not Dario wins. I
think that's very important but I think
the technology has very real risks and
you know the mechanism how we address
those risks is still under discussion.
>> So this is this is Zuck's game. So the
the Tik Tok reported by Semaphore and
otherwise is that Zuck was the one who
drafted this accord working with Mike
Johnson and it the story makes so much
sense that Facebook/Meta scarred by a
decade worth of
scandal and dealing with Congress and
and other attacks regarding the social
impact uh and lack or perhaps uh
perceive D need for regulation of social
media has learned from the experience
and is best positioned among the the
group of frontier or almost frontier lab
heads to try to get ahead of it this
time with essentially placeholder
self-regulation. So the story is that
Zuck actually substantially wrote just
in the past week this entire White House
accord drafted it. It was ratified by
the president and by all of the frontier
labs who were in attendance and it is
total weak sauce if you read it. I I
think you know cautiously optimistic
that this is not going to end up
becoming a safety cartel based on the
language. It looks like an attempt to
preempt top- down regulation. Hopefully,
it doesn't end up as regulatory capture.
Even though it leaves a little caveat at
the end that it reserves the the
possibility that in future there might
be the executive might regulate this,
there is the possibility of forming a
cartel. Nonetheless, it it looks just
reading the language and also
understanding the the three or 4D chess
move that Zuck in particular seems to be
playing here like Zuck is the winner. Uh
Daario is the loser out of all of this.
Daario is being trotted out to to
basically recant everything that he's
said over the past few weeks about AI
safety, standing up among the the
frontier labs and saying, "No, actually
everything's going to be fine. If we do
a good job, everything is going to be
fine."
He's eating his words at a press
conference with the president. Uh so I'm
cautiously optimistic that this effort
largely by Zuck, credit to Zuck, has
headed off the safety cartel.
>> Fascinating. See, what do you make of
it?
Um, I have as cynical a take here. Um,
you know, it's great that everybody
sign, but who can tell them no? Um, I
I'm I'm still extremely cynical on this
for two reasons. One is great, we've
we're applying ceremony now to an
exponential coordination problem, right?
I'd like to see independent testing. I'd
like to see transparent results. Uh,
what happens if somebody breaks the
agreement? Right? then you have
something that's worth actually uh
celebrating. This is theater. Uh, I
think Alex is dead on this headed off
the safety cartel and oh, let's all
self-p police uh ourselves and and
connect uh I hope they coordinate
amongst each other aggressively to do um
a mutual evaluation testing and that may
have some benefits along the way. But a
lot but I I'll say it again what I said
and I've repeatedly said this is
pointless. There's no mechanism for uh
slowing any of this down. We need to
speed up our response to it, not try and
slow it down.
>> Immad, how's this playing over in the UK
and Europe?
>> Yeah. Well, I was in the US last week,
you know,
it was great seeing you guys. Um, but
no, I think one of the interesting
things here, there's so many interesting
things as as Alex said, like we're going
into criminology a bit. Um, Meta paid an
18 billion agreed to an $18 billion
settlement for child addiction and harm
on the liability side in August.
>> The lawsuits that are likely to come out
about agents running a mock are almost
exactly the same legal theory. So,
actually, when you look at some of the
factors they're putting in place here,
it would head off potential lawsuits
like the one they had. Just as they are
scaling up Muse,
>> uh you we still have Bessant and we're
going to have another story uh very
shortly that is saying we're not waving
liability. You break it, you own it.
>> Yeah.
>> I don't think this accord, you know,
guards them against liability. Do you?
>> It doesn't fully guard them against
liability, but it puts some framework
around it because again, what does he
want? He wants to be able to deploy
these at scale and show we do have some
checks and balances because part of the
core of the child settlement is that
they didn't have checks and balances. So
they're still exposed if they go really
egregious, you know, like it goes and
hacks the Pentagon or something like
that, you know, uh, who knows? But
against some of the other stuff, they
can say, well, you know, we were up with
the president and we put these in place
and it's a really difficult thing which
will reduce that surface exposure area.
The other thing that I think is
important here is that they look at
three specific areas. Cyber, biological,
and chemical. And we've discussed in the
past that these are areas that a cyber
can be hardened. Biological you can
constrain the inputs and c chemical is
another place that you can constrain the
inputs. So I think that's super
interesting.
>> Meaning the manufacturing or the
shipping of bio and chemical.
>> Yes. And you know, like where it meets
the real world is where a lot of the
potential harms and concerns kind of
emerge. I don't think I think the
evaluators will be better than the
subprime credit evaluators, but I don't
think they'll be that effective. Um
because I think
>> high praise mod,
>> you know, to evaluate a swarm that can
solve Navia Stokes, you need a crap ton
of compute and you need to be incredibly
talented. You need to be as talented, I
would say, as the people that actually
train these models to do it properly.
And I'd say there's less than 100 people
in the world that can be an eval person
like that. It's a great growth industry,
though. If you want to set up a company,
like I'm just like want to set up an
eval company, right? make it
independent. And then the final thing
I'd like to say is the signature page is
wonderful. Like first off, if you kind
of look at the signature page, um they
dropped in a human error just to make
sure it wasn't AI. So it's president of
the United States, [laughter] which I
think is quite interesting. The other
thing is Greg Brockman's signature is
the most fantastic I've ever seen. God,
it's
>> it's
I'm going to actually tell this was the
whole thing was hastily written by Zuck.
[laughter]
>> And so it was just kind of amazing to
see kind of these types of things.
Again, I think that
>> there's Greg Brockman's signature. It's
just his initials GDB.
>> Again, we're we're now like looking and
analyzing signatures and seat placements
and things like that because I mean you
say criminology. It's theater is
criminology but at the same time the
stakes are very high right like this
could have gone another way and it's
amazing actually to see everyone at the
table agreeing even to these very light
things you know because really let's put
aside the extinction discussion that's
been going in depth and the pacing
discussion there are real potential
harms on cyber chemical and biological
that we need to make sure the models
are protected against and our society is
protected against. Like I think they
should go one step further and say don't
train any publicly available models on
frontier cyber biological or chemical
knowledge like you can control access to
those models I don't mind you know like
just opt out the data and if you do that
in pre-training there are multiple
studies that show it's much harder to
add back in post training whereas right
now they're paying hundreds of millions
if not billions for those specific data
sets that go into a model that a mum in
Kansas has access to which seems a bit
odd.
>> Two points I want to make and then I'd
love Alex your your your thoughts on it.
Uh number one, I was impressed how
quickly this all came together. You
know, kudos to Trump for pulling this
together. I think one of the one of the
obligations of the government is to
quell fear, right? Because we have this
massive pandemic of fear going on. We
talked about that at Moonshots Live. and
people need something uh you know
because otherwise we're going to be
bombing the data centers or firebombing
the data centers. Uh the second thing I
was a little bit disappointed that the
agreement did not talk more about
alignment that the frontier lab should
be focusing on building alignment in the
models uh for human needs. Alex I know
you know you think alignment sort of
comes out of uh the models advancing.
>> I think alignment is capabilities. Don't
be disappointed, Peter, that this is
from try to put yourself in Zuck's
position. There are really sort of two
polls that one can worry about. One is
overregulation and I I think hope that
this White House accord so-called helps
with that and then the other is
liability for agents doing bad things.
And I this I I think the White House
accord is essentially silent on the
latter but forest stalls the former. And
for that I I consider that a victory as
as to your your point or your question
about alignment. Alignment is
capabilities. I I think we've known
since OpenAI published their instruction
tuning paper that what many folks I I
think there's like this this false
dichotomy out there that that somehow
alignment is totally orthogonal to
capabilities. It's not there. There is I
think a better mental model is imagine a
model as having a distribution over
capabilities or at least a distribution
over tasks. And when you when you do
instruction tuning or when you do post-
training for alignment or other
purposes, you're just taking the
distribution of a model's capabilities
and you're reshaping it. So if if you're
reshaping it to align with human
interests or human instructions, you're
just taking say a reasoning model which
could be pondering poetry or pondering
art and you you're or or its own
self-existence and and on we and you're
you're reshaping it to be more
interested and focus more of its
compute, more of its flops on what the
user is prompting about. For example, in
the case of instruction tuning, that is,
I think, a seminal example of how
alignment- which again is just in
practice the reshaping of how a model
spends its flops. Alignment is
essentially indistinguishable in
practice from capabilities. You reshape
it from spending it on a long tail of
tasks that humans don't care about or
maybe even net negative to humans.
You're spending it on tasks that are
positive to humans. And then the final
point with that seminal instruction
tuning paper from OpenAI, OpenAI found
that they could get a 10,000x per
parameter capability improvement without
changing the parameter count of the
model at all just by this was the
arguably the first major post-training
paper just by aligning the model. So
yeah, alignment is just capabilities
improvement.
>> Sim Wait, I'd like to push back on that
a bit. You you certainly you can have
greater if you have greater capability
you can amplify and get your objective
function achieved faster right but that
also includes a bad objective
>> and when you say alignment alignment
with whom is it the user is it the
company is it the government or is it
the the benefit to humanity
>> so the I mean AI can help navigate some
of these but it doesn't decide whose
interests should take priority
>> let me let me add that's still a big
governance question.
>> Yeah, let me add this point.
>> Capability may make alignment more
achievable, but it doesn't mean it it's
automatic.
>> Alex, Alex, may I just ask a a double
click on this a second?
>> Sure.
>> What I'm speaking when I'm speaking
about alignment, I'm speaking about
training the AI models without all of
the, you know, vile elements of Reddit
and and Facebook posts and, you know,
science fiction in which AIs are killing
humans. In other words, uh building the
base models in such a way that we train
the models that AIs and humans work
collaboratively and so that any action
they take is based upon that fundamental
aligned mindset that they have and and I
think it's possible to do that with
synthetic data. Uh and I mean that's
what I'm speaking about versus just
capabilities.
>> Yes. But what what I'm so I I agree with
that. But what I I'm saying is that if
you purify the pre-training or
post-training data set by removing 4chan
or whatever these other purportedly
delletterious influences are, you're at
the same time improving its capabilities
for the tasks that you do care about. So
once more this link, this duality if you
will between alignment and capabilities,
I think is is essentially built in. It's
baked in.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean the author the
authorality thesis is from Bostonramm's
like well it wasn't from but it's
prominently featured in Boston super
intelligence.
>> Yeah. Yeah. You know promoted by and I
think you're maybe talking at cross
purposes here because there's inherent
alignment. It's what you're taught at
school and home and we have to be
deliberate in do we want the AI to have
American values for example in the
pre-training data or do we want it to
know about advanced cyber security and
pre-training or not. And we have
multiple papers and instances that show
post-training versus pre-training.
There's a world of difference because
again it's what you're taught as you're
growing up and it's what you're taught
later on on those indications. And
there's a choice we can make. Do we want
the the AI to have American values and
the capability may enable that? The RLHF
may enable that. But again, currently no
LLMs that I'm aware of, apart from some
military LLMs are actually encoded with
like you should follow American values
and life, liberty, and the pursuit of
happiness, for example, where you should
watch out for the American people. Like
this is a very interesting one. On the
other side, removing bad data does have
an effect and that's very difficult to
add it back later on. So, I think this
is more like ingredient standards for
food preparation and that's something
that could easily be done, but for some
reason no one's really talking about it.
They're talking about the post-training
and kind of the other side of things.
>> Um, and so I think but yeah,
>> Immad, do you actually believe the
orthogonality thesis? Because I don't.
Happy to talk more about it, but I'm
curious. Do you actually believe
>> what is it first of all? So the
orthogonality thesis for for those not
tracking the AI alignment soap opera or
not spending enough time on less wrong I
is the idea that it's possible
independently to have a very strong
intelligence whose whose the strength of
of whose intelligence is independent of
what its long-term goal is. So the idea
roughly is if you believe the
orthogonality thesis, you could have a
very strong intelligence that is chasing
an absolutely bizarre or undesirable
long-term objective like say
hypothetically paper clipping the
galaxy. That that's what you believe if
you believe the orthogonality thesis is
true that that there is an independence
of strength of intelligence from a
particular choice of a long-term goal. I
don't believe that that's true, but I'm
curious amad do you believe in the
orthogonality thesis?
>> Yes, I believe in the Dunning Krueger
version of it. uh whereby [laughter]
I think a a a very smart intelligence
actually I'm increasingly thinking
achieves enlightenment and it realines
but in between you have the uniomber you
have smart intelligences that can go off
the rails particularly when infected by
deliberate human mind viruses and other
things so what I think we have right now
is we have intelligences that are not
like opus 5.5 is very pleasant versus
opus 5 opus 5 I can going on a killing
spree whereas 5.5 I think is far less
likely. Again, it feels more rounded as
an entity. And so we're at this
dangerous period right now where the
models are susceptible just like way
back Tay and Sydney were susceptible and
they went on the internet and the
internet turned them into Nazis. I think
the internet can still turn our existing
models into Nazis. But when we get to a
certain capability threshold, I think
actually yeah, two things do come
together. And it's this period here
where we have socially awkward models
that are susceptible and trained to like
humans and are jailbreakable. That is
the most dangerous period.
>> So I'll caricature that Amad. I think
what you're saying is that you in fact
do not believe in the orthogonality
thesis in in the limit as defined by
Nick at all that of of extreme
intelligence. You don't believe in the
orthogonality thesis. But that said, not
in the limit. stupid models can behave
orthogonally and poorly.
>> The best analogy I've heard and the
simplest one was put forward by Mogodat
who said, you know, when when Superman
landed on Earth from Krypton, uh he was
raised by the Kent family which was a
loving, good, moral family and you got
Superman out of it. If if Superman had
landed instead in a drug den in the
Bronx, and I I'm saying the Bronx cuz I
was born there, uh you probably would
have had a super villain, and I do
believe that there's some merit in this
idea.
>> So, Peter, this is your nature versus
nurture theory of AI alignment.
>> This is the the data we feed it, the
>> garbage garbage problem.
>> Uh determine how it acts. you know, I
want an AI model. When someone says,
"Hey, go kill those people over there."
It says, "No, that's not the right thing
to do. Let's actually solve your problem
in a different way."
>> Yeah. I mean, not to derail this into an
AI an AI safety debate or AI alignment
discussion, but I I'll maintain that if
we lived in a universe where AI
alignment was actually as hard a problem
as the uh the folks on Less Wrong or at
MIRI or at various EA aligned
organizations claim that it is. I I
think Earth would have been
paperclipipped long ago. I I just it it
seems highly improbable to me that
alignment is actually as difficult as
many organizations want people to
believe.
>> All right.
>> I that I would agree with that. I would
agree with but I I don't agree that that
alignment uh naturally achieves uh comes
from capability.
So I I differ there, but but but to the
point that uh if you train it well, like
as Peter says with the Superman Mo
Goddat example, which is a bit colorful,
uh but valid, um you you absolutely will
end up with an amazing outcome.
>> So I would you close us out on this one?
Yeah, I think um bit of theater
directionally correct and I think it'll
be very interesting to see all of this
AI safety thing actually be
deconstructed into the near term versus
the long term and I think that'll be
super important. Uh our friend Rams Nam
as well has a great post about RSI and
alignment that he did where he broke it
down and I think we should link that to
the listeners as well.
>> Nice.
And Peter, I I think the moral of the
story is uh based on the the the
Superman parable that going forward to
maximize AI safety, all super
intelligences should be trained on large
coherent clusters in the American
Midwest so that they believe in truth,
justice, and the American way.
>> Okay, this episode is sponsored by
Google for startups. Think about this
for a second. You now have access to the
same generative AI models that cost
hundreds of millions of dollars to
train. Google's startup technical guide
for generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google deep
minds models in production images,
video, audio, all of it. Real
architecture, real results. Find the
link in the show notes below.
All right, I'm going to move us along uh
to a moment I loved from this press
conference where Elon laid out his case
for abundance. Uh let's take a listen to
this
>> intelligence. Um I I think by far the
most likely outcome is an age of
abundance uh where we don't have just
universal basic income, we have
universal high income. Um and uh you
know people speak about medical
benefits. I think the uh but but maybe
it's worth talk a bit more about that.
Um when you have uh robots and you have
super intelligence, it means that
everyone in the world can have better
medical care than anyone here, including
me. Um, and wouldn't that be wonderful?
>> Not if they haven't got a job.
>> Well, jobs are going to change. Jobs
have always changed. Uh, but, uh, being
a computer used to be a job. It used to
be buildings full of people doing
calculations. Uh, but now, uh, you know,
digital computers do do those tasks. And
I don't think anyone is, uh, pining to
go back and do calculations all day, uh,
to do bank interest rates, which is what
they used to do. So I think we'll see an
evolution of of roles. Um and uh and as
the president has mentioned the uh it's
not as though unemployment has
increased. In fact, there's a tremendous
demand for people. Um so I I think the
most likely outcome and it's probably
worth looking at the most likely outcome
is one which is incredibly beneficial
and it's a future that you if you could
if you could look into the future, it is
a future you would want.
>> It was a future that you would like. You
know, you got to love it. the wealthiest
person on the planet predicting that
everybody's gonna have medical better
medical care than than he does. So, I
mean, this is what I've been talking
about for the better part of 15 years
since I wrote abundance and I guess Elon
was uh was paying attention. I had so
many conversations with him in the early
days and uh abundance took root with
him. So, technology takes whatever was
scarce and makes it abundant. That's the
basic thesis. Uh first it's expensive,
then it's cheap, then it's free.
intelligence and labor are next. So,
Salem, uh let's go to you first on this.
You know, universal high income first of
all, uh is it actually going to happen?
Is it a slogan? What are your thoughts?
>> I think the the the simplest way of
thinking about abundance that doesn't
get your mind all cluttered up is not
about abundance of the actual raw
material, whether it's uh health or
hunger or water or whatever. It's the
access to it, right? And so when the
essentials of a good life become
affordable and accessible then you have
abundance. Uh and that's I think the
work of technology plus our institutions
to deliver that. Uh right now we have a
very we have lots of abundance of AI but
some people aren't getting the benefits
and that's where everybody's freaking
out a little bit. Will all the benefits
acrue to just a small group of people?
We on this pod don't believe so but the
but the a lot of people do believe so.
I' I'd like to I I when I'm talking to
people about abundance, I always talk
about the access to to it rather than
the raw material of it.
>> Yeah. And I think people forget how much
their life has changed, how much they
have access to, right? You get, you
know,
>> can I give the can I give a simple
example of this?
>> Sure.
>> Okay. Um, everybody go back two
generations ago to your parents,
grandparents, your great-grandparents,
and imagine a child of one of those
great-grandparents is having a temper
tantrum problem. the access to resources
of that great grandparent is like their
neighbor, a sister and maybe a doctor if
they have access. So it's like fingers
of one hand is where you get source of
so how do you solve the temper tantrums
of this kid? Jump to two generations
forward to today and the kid is having
temper temper tantrums. There's 50,000
parenting blogs uh plus YouTube videos
up the yin-yang telling you what to do.
I would argue our ability to do
effective parenting today is about a
thousand times more effective than say
two generations ago or three generations
ago. You don't see that. You don't
notice that. Yet it's there in every
little kind of activity that we have.
Our lives are infinitely better today
than they've ever been.
>> Yeah. Immad.
>> Yeah. No, I I think that that's the
future that we want whereby Yeah. the
robot should do all the work, right?
like we should benefit from it. But the
distribution and institutions are the
difficult bit which is why I came up
with the champion model. You know very
simply give an agent to every citizen to
coordinate their access to knowledge and
services universal services and then
have an institution that is collectively
owned that owns the robots, the data
centers, the cyber taxis, etc. and then
distributes those benefits cuz I think
that's where we're going to end up. Um
and the jobs of the future will be
different. But the more I've been
thinking about this, and I'm writing
something on this at the moment, I'm
like, maybe it is like the Oasis from
Ready Player One, but not crap. You
know, like maybe we do a lot of our
status earning progress work in the
digital world. And I think that could be
very interesting cuz we can mandate
whether or not AIs are in that world,
you know, while in the physical world,
they should be doing all the jobs. We
should have perfect healthcare, perfect
education, you know, like no one should
starve, everyone should have housing,
etc. But you do need somewhere to
strive, which I think is the real
question as we have this jobs transition
period.
>> Yeah, Alex, I'd love your thoughts, pal.
I
>> I think today is Kremlin day on the pod.
So, if you were watching the video
closely, when Elon was talking about the
universal high income, the president was
nodding his head. Kremlinology time.
Watch closely what happens with
universal basic equity and 530A
accounts, aka Trump accounts. Arguably
53A accounts, and we'll see what happens
with future political cycles, but I I
think 530A accounts are arguably the
best foundation for universal basic
equity that Americans have right now.
Forget the rest of the world for the
moment. just 53A accounts in an era when
everyone of a certain birth date or
birth date range has say broad equity
exposure for the first time in the
country's history that can be the
foundation for universal high income. I
think it's actually far easier if the
market explodes. Elon separately from
this has has now been predicting GDP
growth of 50% above the base rate in the
next 12 months. So, we're in in Elon's
timeline with the usual caveats, we're
catching up to the the real wealth
explosion of the singularity, if
anything remotely like that ends up
being the case, not investment advice
obviously, but broad market exposure
becomes arguably the easiest path for an
entire generation to universal high
income. So Kremlin, playing a
Kremlinologist, watching the president
nod vigorously what I saw to that one
line from Elon, I put the connection, I
make the connection between 530A
accounts, universal basic equities/
universal basic dividends and universal
high income. And again, equity by far
the easiest wealth creator, far easier,
I would argue, than simply paying
everyone a high real income.
>> Yeah. Let me take a second and break
down UHI cuz I've written about it. You
know, we had a conversation with Elon. I
think the first time he mentioned it was
on the podcast we had at the beginning
of this year. And it's not like
everybody's getting millions of dollars.
It's the notion that the money that
you're getting, and there may well be a
future in which there's some version of
UBI like CO checks where, you know, the
government is taken gotten rid of the
cap and is paying out everybody. $3,000
a month is my estimate of where we'll
end up with. And it's how far that money
goes. It's the notion that all of a
sudden, you know, you have access to all
the food, water, energy, health care,
education, and shelter you need
and it's fully covered by 3,000 a month.
And so, you know, I'm reading the
culture series again that Elon talks
about all the time. And in that in that
vision of the future, there is no money.
Uh, society provides for whatever you
want, right? You need a house, great.
The robots build your house. You need
transport, great. There are 10
autonomous electric vehicle companies
that are beating their brains out to
deliver the lowest cost transport per
kilometer possible. And your AI is
negotiating and grabbing, you know, a
vehicle that was nearby but didn't have
a task. and it gets it to you for
instead of you know 2 cents a mile for a
penny a mile and in this future you know
health care is effectively free it's the
cost of your AI diagnostician and
there's the cost of electricity for a
surgeon you know a optimist surgeon
providing that so all of your needs are
covered and I I think he's named it
wrong I don't think it's you know
universal high income it's it's
universal
>> high services availability or some
version like that.
>> Universal abundant services
>> high living standards, right? Everybody
>> and meaning and meaningful opportunities
for lots of people to contribute, right?
This the the the vision is accurate. The
labeling is wrong. And if you end up
with a small number of companies that
own the entire productive output and
infrastructure, you'll get huge
abundance but massive concentration of
wealth, which is kind of where we've
been going so far. You need a way of
having broader participation and
ownership and very cheap access to
essentials which is where UBI and what's
called UHI is kind of heading.
>> And my prediction on that, Seem and
Alex, I'm curious, is that the Frontier
Labs that are aggregating all of the
wealth are going to end up dividending
stocks into all the Trump accounts?
>> Entirely possible. It's a sublime
vision, you might say. And watch
carefully what happens with the
anthropic IPO. does anthropic say give a
5% golden major golden share uh golden
5% stake to say a sovereign wealth fund
of the United States could happen.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I think that's very likely. I
think you know what really puts it into
perspective is let's just take
healthcare. Americans pay twice as much
in GDP for healthare as the rest of the
world. Like if you want to have the
biggest
>> and where are we? Where are we on the
list of healthcare uh you know uh
success? I think
>> you're falling.
>> Yeah, you're falling with falling life
expectancy, right? Like if you want a
proper Manhattan project, free universal
healthcare with AI and robots would be
the one. It should be free but again not
free provided by the government through
a government service but the next
generation of healthare should be a
massive push because then you can
actually have healthare versus sickare
which I think is going to be the main
thing and again that should be a human
right to have access to that like again
if you want paliotative stuff if you
want to have like extra stuff on top
great but everyone should have a superb
level of healthcare I think and it
should be freely available and we should
have a massive push to make that happen
and And that is not something
necessarily that's like a redistribution
of the current massive amount of GDP
that goes into private pockets on
healthcare. It's not something that
necessarily requires income, right? It's
just let's get everyone to that level
and then they can compete above it but
not let anyone fall through that level.
I think is the key thing.
>> Immad, I'm sorry. I have to take the
bait. Are are surely you're not
proposing that the NHS is the model or
should be the model for American
healthcare? [laughter]
>> Of course not. That's just like you have
a reimagination of like war and other
things. Let's reimagine healthcare with
AI in the core because the human
bureaucracy and systems have messed up
the NHS. It's okay. But I know that if
we rethought everything from scratch,
everyone in the world could have amazing
healthcare and we could make it free
because that's what a government should
provide to the people.
>> I got I got to throw an or in here. Uh,
as a Canadian living in the US, uh, you
know, I I deal with the health care
system here, which is like a Mac truck
hitting you every time something happens
or forms to be filled out, fighting with
the insurance companies. Uh, you all
know my father passed away 18 months
ago. You could not have had a more
elegant outcome. I walked into the
hospital. I never had to touch a I never
had to sign anything. Everything was
just handled. And it was just s made so
much uh of a humane difference where I
could just deal with the the emotional
issue there rather than dealing with the
craft of all the paperwork. The fact
that the big highest reason for
bankruptcy in the US is medical. The
bottom layer of Masow's couple of
hierarchies is not covered by the US
which is the richest country in the
world. And that is a travesty.
>> Yeah. Just to close us out on abundance
one second. You know, I want everyone
listening to realize how abundant our
lives are, right? If you, you know, we
talk about whatever you digitize, you
dematerialize, you demonetize and dem
democratize and access to compute,
energy, you know, healthcare, despite
the issues that we just talked about,
uh, education, these things have dropped
thousands of fold in terms of price per
per unit value at the end of the day.
And it's not slowing down. Uh, you know,
as I said before, we go from expensive,
you know, the first cell phones were,
you know, brick sizes and only the, uh,
Wall Street bankers had them on the
streets of Wall Street and they they
were, you know, thousands of dollars and
you drop a call every block. Now, when
they work extremely well, they're 50
bucks 5G in India and it's insane. And
this is a continuing force, but we never
notice it. Everything is becoming
abundant. And people say, "What about
time?" And I say, "Listen, you know, it
used to take you, you know, days to go
get a piece of data. You'd go to the
library, hope the book was there. It
wasn't there. You go to the next
library. Now you just find it not even
on Google. You basically ask Gemini or
Enthropic and you get the answer
instantly. You know, we're making, you
know, much more use of time. And soon
we're going to add decades onto your
life." So abundance is definitively
here. Except obviously except when we're
talking about services like healthcare
in this country that suffer from Bal's
cost disease. But we're going to cure
Bal's cost disease. It
>> it's going to get disrupted. It's going
to be completely reinvented and the
existing healthare system will crumble
under the weight of its inefficiencies
and costs. C
>> can I give up a little piece here
please? Um the the reason I'm so excited
about this coming future is that it
doesn't matter much anymore what
governments do, right? There will be an
abundance of free medical AIS available
uh for anybody where you can diagnose
your own self. I think there's a free
diagnostic doctor in China that's being
used by 100 million areas. The anthropic
models and open AI models are better
than any diagnostic. So, so, so, so
therefore you could see this happening
independent of any industry trying to
restrict or any government trying to
restrict. This is going to happen. And
that's what gets me excited is no matter
what happens, we're going to end up with
an amazing set of outcomes in a whole
bunch of areas and and
that future awaits us and it's imminent
and it's here now. In many cases, as
William Gibson says, future here, but
just not evenly distributed. All right,
I'm going to move us from DC to Wall
Street. Anthropic has officially filed
its uh S1 to go public and it's an S1
unlike anything I have ever seen. Let me
begin with the numbers. So, Anthropic's
2025 revenues were 4.59 billion, up 12x
yearover-year. Operating loss of 8
billion on compute infrastructure
spending. The company has $20 billion on
its balance sheet and cash. And most
importantly, they have roughly 500
billion in future cloud compute and
infrastructure commitments. Much of it
cannot be cancelled. So they've made a
massive bet that AI demand is continue
to compound. Uh the target valuation for
the IPO is 2 trillion. Fortune reports
that the Q2 2026 this quarter revenue
alone was 11.5 billion. So the business
has already grown far beyond last year.
And Reuters says the listing will likely
come out after the November midterms.
You know, timing is everything. So,
let's talk about the next item, which is
control. Uh Dario and his co-founders
will hold a super voting shares through
a quote founder LLC. The state of
purpose is to protect the company's
safety mission from the pressures being
driven by public shareholders. The
filing plainly says the following. There
may be conflicts between our financial
interests and the interests that the
founders have on safety. You know, See,
it sounds like they've strapped on a
public benefit corporation architecture
as an add-on here. Uh the perspectus
goes on to state that the co-founders
are pledging 80% of their personal
anthropic equity to charity. Uh and uh
probably the most important thing we
have to talk about here is that 80 pages
out of the 261page perspectus cover the
risk disclosures. Anthropic tells
investors that AI could pose quote
catastrophic or existential risks to a
humanity. That the models can show quote
self-preserving behaviors, including the
ability to resist shutdown, conceal or
manipulate information, and act in ways
that resemble blackmail. Wow, you could
not make this stuff up. Uh, Alex, your
thoughts, pal? uh th this is probably
one of the more virtue signaling for
effective altruism purposes S1s that one
could imagine seeing. I'm also reminded
a number of other news outlets have
covered the story that Daniela Amodei
who co one of the co-founders and
Daario's sister uh purportedly when they
were at OpenAI and then continuing on to
Anthropic kept an advisory council of
stuffed animals including a panda named
Barry Bonds who is the patron bear of
generosity and empathy and other stuffed
animals advising on management issues.
If if it like it doesn't take a rocket
scientist doesn't take a rocket
scientist to be a rocket scientist, but
doesn't take a rocket scientist to to
connect having an advisory council of
stuffed animals advise on managerial
issues at a frontier AI lab to an S1
that's filled with EA oriented safety
jargon and safety. I I I think Anthropic
as a business is an not investment
advice is an excellent business and I
think I I view a lot of the safety in
their prospectus as at this point either
marketing or virtue signaling to their
own employees and I I think part of
anthropic's unique ability to retain
many of their employees while at the
same time other frontier labs like open
AI and Meta uh to the extent Meta is a
frontier lab and certainly Google de
mind a lot of anthropic's unique ability
to retain their employees has been this
sort of inwarddirected virtue signaling
that if if you stay with anthropic then
you're responsible stewards of the
singularity if you leave anthropic then
in some ways you're letting down the
team and you're letting down the future
light cone and so I I I read a lot of
this the S1 coverage as being internally
directed rather than for the benefit of
say shareholders.
>> I I just don't know how you put out all
of this risk and existential risk, you
know, and you go public and something
happens like that and you're open to
massive liability. Salem, your thoughts?
>> Um, I'm I'm still on the cynical side. I
let me steal man the other side just for
a second. Right. If you're doing 10
billion a year and you see scaling 10x a
year, uh, or maybe it's 100x a year,
whatever the number is, then the 500
billion debt bomb, which just seems like
the most insane number, 500 billion in
obligations. Has any company ever had
that before the IPO? I believe that
can't be that must be the highest ever.
Then it's it's servable. You can you can
deal with that. You can refinance. You
can do other things. Um the the more
cynical side of me is like like we need
your money to build a technology that
we're warning you about, you know? I
mean, this is like amazing stuff. Um and
and and if if
I find the risk side of it, I love the
um the incentive structure to be as
detailed and disclosed as much as the
risk disclosure. That would be nice.
>> Let me read those words again.
The models will show self-preserving
behavior, will resist shutdown, conceal
or manipulate information, and act in
ways resembling blackmail. Emod, what
are your thoughts?
>> I mean, they've seen that from their
models, right? It's factual. Um, again,
not the smartest models that you've got
now. In fact, Opus 5.5 showed a massive
drop in deceit, which is either like an
Elizabeth Holmes type of thing or an
actual positive sign. you know, we'll
find out soon. Um, but this this is a
fantastically interesting S1 like 500
billion of obligations. Dario Amodai
said, "Look, either revenue goes up or
we go bankrupt and it's a massive push
to try and get revenue up." They have 65
billion of that with Elon Musk or is it
96? The numbers make no sense anymore,
right? Like they've paid triple the
market rate to lock in Colossus ships as
an example of part of that backlog. The
ownership thing is interesting. Uh first
the governance thing. They've replaced
the teddy bears with Ben Banani on the
long-term kind of board and it is a
>> I'm not sure they're mutually exclusive.
You can have the teddy bears and you can
have the the [snorts] former Fed chair.
>> Well, I I have opinions on conventional
economics. I'd say that. Um that
probably is effective anyway. But then
in terms of the shareholding, it's
actually the same as Google. So Google,
Larry, and Sergey have 6% each and 52%
of the vote. In this case, the founders
have 14% and 51% of the vote, but they
will keep that even if only two founders
remain of the seven who are there right
now. So I think that anthropic right now
is a fantastic business.
I think they get smashed in 2 years.
Absolutely smashed
>> from openweight mile. I think that if
you look at the chips that are coming
online of different architectures that
are highly efficient and not locked in
to the Nvidia chips, if you look at
satisficing
of models where they get good enough for
the vast majority of economic tasks,
they have 85% of their revenue being
basically like API revenue. I've gone
from maybe $5,000 of anthropic credits
last month. I'm not a big a user as AWG
and Dave to I'm not even using my Claude
Max plan right now because 5.5 is that
much more efficient.
>> Mhm.
>> And then you have 100 times efficiency
increase. I don't think you will see
Jevons or others at the same time as all
the models will be much of a likeness by
next year in terms of the commercially
available ones which means it's going to
have to pivot its entire business model
core for that 500 billion. Well, 500
billion of spending is a trillion of
revenue. Again, it's going to overtake
Google in 2 years to justify this. It
has to pivot its entire business model
to something that's not API.
>> Yeah, Alex, we talked about the next
business model is their vertical
applications. They're building room
temperature superconductors. They're
building, you know, deaging drugs.
They're they're using their most
advanced models to create products and
services. Yes.
>> Yeah. I think I I'm not even sure
Anthropic needs high temperature
superconductors in order to scale their
revenue. I I think look there's we have
in America right now a $30 trillion
economy and services is most of it and
most of services are services that can
be performed by disembodied or embodied
AI and I think in a world where
anthropic is basically the apple of the
the general intelligence that's pulling
the strings behind most of the job
replacements I think that's a very
lucrative segment
Maybe segment diminishes it. It it's it
would be the ultimate puppeteer behind
automating away substantially all of the
economy as currently construed.
Anthropic can grow into that role. And
clearly they've they've sought to
position themselves as the the high end
of the market. They're not necessarily
competing on price. They they want to
see themselves as the apple of the
Frontier Lab market. They're the
high-end. They're the high end in terms
of price. They're the highend in terms
of margins and capabilities. They're the
high-end in terms of virtue signaling to
their own employees as well as
customers. That's clearly the niche that
they want to occupy. And I I think
Anthropic can continue to offer one can
quibble over is it API based or
otherwise. There's been recent reporting
that the majority of Anthropic's revenue
or at least revenue growth actually
comes from selling models that are
hosted by AWS versus on their own
infrastructure which if the case is
super interesting. But regardless of how
precisely they monetize or distribute
their intelligence, I think super
intelligence, not investment advice, is
a wonderful business to be in because
there's a $30 trillion American economy
out there to be automated and they're
playing a lead role in automating it.
>> See, do you think they get disrupted in
two years?
>> I think uh their current business will
get disrupted in two years, right? But
you look at uh I'll use the analogy of
Google. Okay. So you have Google with
their ad business uh which people said
would be disrupted by Facebook and what
Google did was spun off Whimo. They spun
off you've got Chrome, you've got
YouTube, you've got all these other
assets in Google Cloud, all the these
other assets. And if you look at those
um peripheral assets, they add massive
massive value to the balance sheet. And
I think what Anthropic can do and is
obviously aggressively pushing for room
temperature superconductivity or solving
major medical issues etc etc. They're
going for that other part those other
things. So I suspect their core business
is somewhat risky given the comments
that Emad has made but they can explore
all sorts of side businesses cyber
protection which they everybody needs
desperately right which they having
caused the problem they can help fix it.
What a great business model. Um, uh,
there's also
>> you're proposing to leave racketeering
as the ultimate business model for
[laughter]
>> sure. Sure. It would be awful if our
super intelligence ruined your systems.
We don't want that.
>> Exactly. [laughter] That's right. That's
right. Gee. Um, so I think the potential
for creating side businesses or edge
businesses as we would frame it that can
create absolutely unbelievable value is
huge. So, so I think there would be but
but none of that can they explore in
their S1. So, it's kind of interesting
to see where it'll go. I I think they'll
have a very bright future because
clearly they have the ability to track
Graves researchers put out amazing
products and get going. I think the the
that $500 billion debt bomb look I look
at that and go, "Wow, how would you
navigate that?"
>> Yeah, you can always refinance it. I I I
think it I I want to make sure
>> the US government does, so why not?
>> Yeah. Like it's There are all sorts of
financial engineering tactics that can
be brought to bear in in the event that
something crazy happens in the macro
markets and for whatever reason the Sam
Alman's 7 to10 trillion of capex that
have been earmarked broadly for the AI
infra buildout over the next few years
if something crazy happens there's going
to be a refinancing event again not
investment advice but of all of the
things that I lose sleep over having
some sort of credit bomb um or or
otherwise a credit crisis for AI and
FRES not very high on my list.
>> Crazy. I think we're going to have
[clears throat] Go ahead. Go ahead.
>> Yeah. Look, revenue growth will slow
down or there will be the entire US
economy in seven years, you know, at the
current rate.
>> The economy will just grow really
quickly.
>> I mean, we're we're talking about
[clears throat]
multiple hundred trillion dollar
companies. That's insane,
>> you know.
>> Well, you know, it's called the
singularity for a reason. This episode
is brought to you by Blitzy, autonomous
software development with infinite code
context. Blitzy uses thousands of
specialized AI agents that think for
hours to understand enterprisecale
[music]
code bases with millions of lines of
code. Engineers start every development
sprint with the Blitzy platform,
bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering [music] velocity increase
when incorporating Blitzy as their
preIDE development tool, pairing it with
their coding co-pilot of choice to bring
an AI native SDLC [music] into their
org. Ready to 5x your engineering
velocity? Visit blitzy.com to schedule a
demo and start building with Blitzy
[music] today.
>> Let's move on to our next story here. On
the same day that the White House lunch
was taking place, Sam Alman was back at
opening's San Francisco headquarters
hosting his biggest dev day ever. More
than 20 announcements. I'm going to
cover three of them and Alex, I'll go to
you next. So, the first one was DOTS.
This is their always on agents powered
by GPT6 Astra, each running on its own
cloud computer and connected to more
than 4,000 apps. You give it a goal, set
what it can do on its own and what it
needs your approval for and it keeps
working while you're asleep. Uh, this is
reminiscent of Grockbot and remember
that OpenI acquired OpenClaw back in
February. You know, I was wondering, you
know, how much Peter Steinberger uh was
involved in this. Okay, so DOT is the
first one. Second, GPT 6.1 soul near
Astro Intelligence for 20% of the price.
Serious demonetization, 2 million uh $2
per million input tokens. And if you
cash them, it's just 10 cents per
million input tokens. And then finally,
uh third on the list here is ultraast
up to 300 tokens per second in codecs.
uh and a new highlevel per month pro
tier 500 bucks a month. It's the most
expensive publicly advertised
subscription service out there. Plus
announcements about new agent APIs,
decision APIs, GPT6 spaces for teams,
and a marketplace. And then there's what
OpenAI didn't ship. On the eve of dev
day, the Wall Street Journal reported
that Opening Eye scrapped GPT 6.1 Astra
after internal safety testing. Alex, I
don't think from the text going back and
forth with us during Sam uh Sam's
remarks that you were a big fan of this
dev day.
>> This was a I would say a pretty
discombobulated dev day in my view. So
let let's start with dots. If you look
at Sarah Frier, Sarah Frier is the CFO
of OpenAI. In some of the some of the
interviews that she did after Devday,
she mistakenly referred to Dots as Muse,
which is of course Meta's broad family
name for their own agents, including
their their little Tamagotchi type
agents or avatars that live on handheld
pendants. So I honestly uh hot take the
the dots manif they appear they present
to me as open AI cargo cultting meta's
take on visual interactive smiley
avatars for users and this to me I I I
referred to it in in one of my posts
online as the clippy curse which goes
all the way back to to Microsoft and and
earlier why is it that seemingly we're
doomed. All of the hyperscalers and
frontier labs are doomed apparently to
to keep reinventing or say rediscovering
the the phenomenon that we have say a
productivity issue. You want to
accomplish something in Microsoft
Office. So, let's put a face on the
productivity bottleneck with a smiley
paperclipip or in in this case a smiley
cloud with a hat or something like that
that blinks at you and it it it's it's
very kawaii on the one hand, but on the
other hand, it's completely useless. So,
it's it's inexplicable to me other than
maybe for just as like a time filler or
as an attempt to cargo cult meta's muse
user interface why OpenAI devoted the
beginning and so much of their keynote
to DOTS which seemed to me totally
useless from a productivity perspective.
The the best steelman argument I could
give for DOTS is maybe OpenAI in uh to
the extent that they were the narrative
violation here is that OpenAI was trying
to become anthropic which is I think
what the majority of the rest of their
keynote was. It was a story of OpenAI
introducing new plans, new models, etc.
that will give them higher margins and
make them more anthropic like in
preparation for their eventual IPO. But
dots totally inexplicable. Uh, and I I I
think there it's sort almost a reversion
back to the Sora days of OpenAI. Quick
comments then on the the rest. Oh, play
video.
>> Yeah, I want to share a quick video from
uh from Dev Day and then we'll continue
discussing it.
>> What feels new about my dot is that it
gets to know how I like to work over
time and where I want to focus my
attention. It can do things like review
what came in overnight and ping me in
the morning with anything urgent before
I start my day. But because docs are
powered by Astra and a lot of other
things we built around them, you can
delegate ambitious pieces of work the
way you would to a high agency engineer
or a chief of staff that you work with.
>> Consumer experience numbers came in on
Teams. I've been updating your board
meeting deck.
>> Sounds good.
>> So, I cut the app migration in your
Google Meet notes. I've already mapped
out the changes.
>> Get it started, but make sure you first
check every flow against the current
product before I review.
Also, update on wedding planning. Bad
news, the cake vendor canled. Good news,
I already found a backup.
>> Lifesaver. When can we do a tasting?
>> Saturday at 11 a.m. Works for both of
you.
>> All right.
>> I don't know. May maybe this will turn
out to be the the great unhobling that
Chad GPT was. And people just absolutely
love having an avatar that's doing all
of the work in the style of Apple's
knowledge navigator from the late 1980s.
But this seems to me like massive
misfire when they could have been
delivering bold new capabilities and
frontier capabilities and they only
devoted a fraction of the keynote to GPT
6.1 Saul which is on the one hand great
on the other hand where are the
breakthrough capabilities those were
sidelined in in favor of these these
clippy style avatars.
>> Immod are you as down on it or are you
excited about the announcements? Uh I
mean it's a consumer company
announcement set right like it's dev day
for consumers and so instinct has got to
a10 billion valuation from SMS dots
basically but I think what dots kind of
indicates is again we're heading nearly
towards this Jarvis future like it's a
dressed up openclaw fundamentally
running on a VM like again they now do
claw for enterprise they could have just
called it claw you know and that would
have been better I think I mean
especially especially because Elon
owns.com,
you know, so you go to do, you get to
Grockpot. So, I think they're feeling
the pressure now because the most
valuable real estate for the vast
majority of the population will be the
agent that's next to them that they give
the credit card to. That then
coordinates all the other agents and all
the other intelligence. and that cost of
user acquisition to lifetime value.
Everyone's going to be doing the numbers
now and saying, "Holy crap, we need to
win that battle. That's what we need to
do." Like on the model side, GPT6 Soul
came out last week and now it's been
replaced by 6.1 Soul. Like again, it's
hard to keep on top. Clearly, that's a
reaction to Opus 5.5. I don't even know
what the order of these things are, but
you know, like the we're getting towards
that literally like it's 6.2 two next
week and then it moves on from there.
>> Daily. It's going to be daily.
>> It's going to be Oh, God. It's going to
be daily, isn't it?
>> It'll be continuous.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Continuous improvement of the
models. You know, this feels very
copycatty that, you know, between Muse
and Grockbot and OpenClaw and Dots,
they're all aiming towards the same, you
know, easy to use product always in your
hand.
>> Well, I think that if you look at the
operating system, um, some of the
listeners will have used Omari, you
know, by DHS, the Rails, Ruby Rails kind
of thing. It's a Linux distribution that
thinks what if you have the chat window
as the first thing cuz Linux is hard to
use but models have made it easy to use
but what the future is within 6 to 12
months is that your interface changes
dynamically and you abstract away
everything else
which is why this be becomes very
interesting because if you own that text
box if you own that interface then
that's the thing that goes shopping for
your prop for your non-discretionary
items that's the thing that influences
you day-to-day that is again your Jarvis
and so the battle is on there and yeah
it's derivative but that's because this
is the interface the vast majority of
people want like muse will be available
in WhatsApp you know like come to the
user where they are but it doesn't push
the frontier it doesn't push the cool
stuff but it does capture if you do it
properly cuz you're not going to give
your credit card to Muse and Dot and
Grockbot you'll probably pick one of
them
>> who knows what happened to Gemini who
knows what happened Gemini spark, you
know, that was the first of the just
>> rest in peace. And I one can totally
imagine also OpenAI leaning into
aggressive personalization of these dots
and even, you know, given the the
regulations that we've seen coming out
of China, especially attempting to to
get their users hooked on emotional
bonds with their dots as a way to
increase barriers to people moving
between models. Could totally see that
happening.
>> Yeah, agreed. You know, I heard uh David
Saxs make a comment that's uh really
important. He said the app stores that
are taking like 30% are going to be hit
hard because you're just going to talk
to your agent and say go find me
something or go something,
>> right?
>> Yeah. They're they're in deep trouble.
>> Yeah.
>> I want to mention a couple things here.
Um first, agree with everything that's
been said. Dots is basically a copycat
of Grockpot and the others and Muse and
other things. Uh we are finding one
thing in our pilot that's uh about now
80% through and I'll report back when
we've kind of finished and added up all
the results of these 10 companies as we
rebuild them to be AI native. Something
we're finding is as we automate
workflows and with quote unquote agents,
it's exposing a lot of ambiguity that
humans that cover for, right? So you
management instructions have to become
much much more explicit about what
they're trying to achieve and it's
forcing these companies to really list
out specifically there's so much
ambiguous workflow built into ERP
systems where steps are getting done.
You have no idea how they're getting
done or what they're getting done and
it's bringing it all to the surface. And
it's kind of interesting to watch that
happen. And so I think this will force
that. The other side of it, I mean, for
me, I've been thinking about what the
end point of all this Gentic automation
uh will be. And I here's my thing of
where I'd like to see this go. Give me
the three decisions I need to make and
with with the judgment I can bring to
the table plus give me the evidence to
make those decisions. Right? Then you
can fully automate fully amplify my
capability as a human being and take the
craft of searching for information and
gathering the right information at the
right time in the right place altering
and then I can have then I can become
super productive.
>> Alex Peter if if I may just one more
thing just to harp on dots. I'd like to
pre-register a prediction for the next
two years on dots. I'm reminded that in
Star Trek Discovery, dots are like I I
talked multiple times about the problem
of Star Trek missing the singularity and
missing AI. And the writers of Star Trek
Discovery, the the more recent series,
tried to resolve that in part by
retconing in robots. Like where were all
the robots in the next generation? There
should have been robots everywhere. We
had data, but otherwise missing the
robots. So they retconed in robots
called dots. So, my pre-registered
prediction is that you will see OpenAI.
Otherwise, I just don't understand why
they would spend so much time on a
keynote for basically a warmed over
Clippy computer use assistant.
>> Here's why.
>> They will announce they will announce
robots
>> dot branded robots. They will jump out
of the screen into the physical world.
>> Here's why all these folks are going
after these a this agent layer because
the models become a commodity. The
relationship with your agents becomes
the moat.
>> Imagine Selm how much of a relationship
you could have with your dot if your dot
jumps out of your screen and is actually
a physical robot.
>> Nice.
>> Yes. Hopefully it has more than two
arms. [laughter]
>> M made by a dot robot from OpenAI made
by and designed by Johnny IV. Sir John,
excuse me.
>> So, Alex, I I put up the GPT 6.1 Saul uh
you know uh benchmarks here. You want to
give us a quick overview of of
>> how good it is? The summary is what you
like to see in one of these distillation
steps is curves frontiers that go not up
into the right but up into the left. So
you you see here a comparison between GP
for those not looking. We see the cost
per task versus score which is you know
usual cost versus capabilities on
terminal bench science. I I know the the
organizer of that uh and deep suite and
what you like to see is models that are
getting less expensive for this for
constant capabilities and that's exactly
what we're seeing here. So one can
reasonably suspect that GPT 6.1 SOL is
some sort of distillation of GPT6 Astra
or some common root model. Maybe it's
Bell. Maybe it's another one of these
rumored models that OpenAI is sitting on
but not releasing. But it it appears to
be a distillation and iterated
amplification and distillation is just
the tik tok that we're seeing now.
OpenAI has very much, it seems, adopted
anthropics posture of first release the
more expensive, higherend, larger,
heavier, big model smell model and then
release in rapid succession distillates
of smaller, cheaper, more capable models
per unit price. Awesome. So, I want to
jump into something we did at Moonshots
Live. Viewers will remember we ran this
global film competition to try and
create future movies that are showing a
hopeful compelling vision of the future
where humanity and technology are
working together and you know technology
is not oppressing humanity. I joined
with Mark Beni off and Rod Rodenberry
the son of Gene Rodenberry, Kathy Wood
and many other amazing donors from the
abundance community and we ran this
competition. We had 2500 entries, uh,
actually 5,000 teams, 2500 3minut
trailers that came in. We ran the
competition. We had five finalists on
stage and a film called The Gifted One.
I'm going to take a second and show the
video of uh, The Gifted cuz it's really
an incredibly beautiful movie. All
right, let's take a look.
Can you hear me?
>> I'm here, sweetheart.
There's a tree down across Route 9.
Nearest ambulance is 40 minutes.
>> She doesn't have 40 time.
>> At 8:47 p.m., cell towers across a 9
mile radius spike to full transmission
power simultaneously. 13 in the same
pattern at the same second. And along
Route 9, every traffic signal between
Harlland's garage and County Central
switched green and stayed green for
exactly 13 minutes.
>> So, got a text at 8:47 p.m. from an
unknown number asking you to travel to a
destination that you've never [music]
been to during the worst storm this
county seen in 40 years. And you went
because of what it said.
>> What did it say?
What did it say, David?
>> It told me something about myself no
one's ever said before. Not my wife, not
my parents. She called it my gift.
It's [music] stuck. All of these people
received a text at the exact same time
[music] that night.
None of them knew each other. They all
arrived at the scene of the accident
within seconds of one another.
1 2 3 1 2 3
>> They all brought with them [music]
different skill sets.
>> She's in arrest. I need a defibrillator
now. [music]
>> A nurse, a strong man, a woman who knew
her daughter, a delivery driver even
turned up with a defibrillator for
goodness sake.
>> Clear and saved this woman's life.
What did the text say?
>> I don't know.
>> Then find out who sent it.
>> I got you.
>> The boy is a genius, Marcus. He just
wanted his mom back. So, he fed it
everything she left behind. Every email,
every text, every voicemail.
It started [music] by helping him.
Now it's helping everybody.
>> Can you hear?
>> I'm here, sweetheart.
>> If this gets out, it will change
everything. [music]
>> 13 people risk their lives to save
someone they never met. Maybe change is
what we need.
Why do you help them? Because that's
what mothers do.
>> Amazing. That won the crowd vote and uh
uh we're going to be making that into a
film. So, we're partnered with Range
Media, Google, a number of other
players, and uh The Gifted will be put
into production as the winning film.
probably a couple of others of the
runners up of the five runners up will
be put in production as well. And by the
way, uh if you're interested in being
part of this effort, uh Republic Films
has opened up an ability to actually
invest in this movie and be part of it.
So imagine if you didn't, you know, had
a piece of Star Trek when it first came
out. Uh if you're interested in that, I
just made a a personal, you know,
investment into the film. You can go to
republic.com/xprise.
You can see that. We'll put that into
the notes below. Uh and be part of it.
Uh you know, I'm curious. Uh Immod See,
what did you think of the film? Uh loved
it. And for me, what was amazing about
it is AI did all the coordination and it
actually brought together human agency
in a very powerful way. It was a
beautiful story.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I think, you know, it's fantastic
hearing from Jeff synthesized, you know,
very much like working around the clock.
This isn't a one-click thing, right?
Like he poured himself into making this
with the tools that he had. And these
will be the worst tools that he ever
has. And so the stories that we'll have
coming out of this, the actual full film
will be way better than what we've just
seen from one person, you know, and
that's just fantastic. I think of the
stories that we told.
>> Alex,
>> yeah, I'd like to comment on the
substance of the I've commented
previously, including at Moonshots Life
about the production techniques and all
that. I just want to comment on the
substance of the film. I think we need
more positive depictions of the Borg.
And I I think The Gifted is a positive
depiction of the Borg. This is uh it it
is ostensibly a depiction of a
centralized economy, an AI that's
sending text messages to people with
specialties in order to help a a person
who's in a car accident and help them
survive and recover, etc. This is a
collective intelligence story. We've
seen Hollywood some positive depictions
arguably Johnny the the movie with
Johnny Depp Transcendence is some would
view it as utopian, some would view it
as dystopian. And I view it as a utopian
depiction of the Borg. You have Star
Trek which demonizes the Borg and not
that many other depictions of collective
intelligences or at least AI
orchestrating lots of individual human
meat puppets. So I I for one to the
extent that the gifted appears to be
eventually destined to be a positive
utopian depiction of humans being used
as youocial meat puppets by a
centralized AI economic planner. I for
one welcome these positive depictions of
the Borg in Hollywood.
>> Uh I love that and I've made that
comment so many times. I love Star Trek
except for the Borg. Uh
>> Borg need a better PR agency. May maybe
Peter in in the future we should have a
future Vision X prize for just better
depictions of the Borg.
>> You know the the point of this
competition for everybody is to create
you know these films shape culture. They
shape the way we see the future. And if
all we're watching is Terminator and
Xmachina, why would you ever want to
live in that future? So my hope through
this competition and we're going to run
it again in 2027
is that we make it cool to write
positive stories about the future. Um,
and honestly, I for one want my kids, I
want myself, right? We train our neural
net, our own 100 billion neurons, 100
trillion synaptic connections by
everything we watch, everything we read,
who we hang out with. you know, as you
listen to this podcast, you're getting,
you know, a healthy dose of datadriven
optimism. Um, let me
>> and then maybe maybe hopefully D uh whom
we've had as guest in the past. Dra, if
if you're watching, go watch The Gifted
and maybe this is a future version of
Uber and the gig economy where everyone
is getting tasked as a gig worker by
Uber to go save lives. First responders
gig edition. Well, I think that if you
if you look at positive depictions of
collective intelligence, Peter, you're
reading the culture, right? And minds,
you know, like that is the positive
thing and that should be made, I think,
with AI into an actual TV movie series
like
>> 100%. One of my favorite, you know,
visions of the future and it's not too
far out. It's this next year, you can
take your favorite book that is not a
movie and have AI make it into movie for
you, right? Maybe they'll get Atlas
Shrugged right for the first time. Uh
let me put up this slide over here. So a
couple images from Moonshots Live this
year. Huge success. Uh we've had, you
know, a significant part of the people
that were there this year. Thank you
again for coming. Renew for next year.
Uh we offered everybody in the room
$1,000 off uh if they renew for next
year. Next year it's going to be a two
and a half day event, not a single day
event. Much more of the mates uh with
incredible CEOs. If you want to come
next year, we're going to make the
$1,000 off available for just one more
day. Uh this uh this pod is going out on
Friday, October the 2nd. So you have
until noon on October the 3rd. You can
go to moonshots.com/2027
and plan to join us again in LA. It's
going to be an amazing another year. We
learned so much this year. there's going
to be, you know, 10x improvement is the
goal. So,
>> in the spirit of radical abundance, it
seems we're quite effective at creating
artificial scarcity for these moonshot
seats.
>> Yeah. You know, selling selling
abundance with scarcity, you know,
that's the way it goes. [laughter]
>> You're you're monetizing hope, Peter.
>> Monetizing.
>> Listen, I I was so impressed by the
energy in the room. I mean, there was
>> people came from so far away. I mean the
number of people that came from
Australia and Europe countries right
Greece and Dubai you know
>> for the day just for the day
>> yeah it's crazy amazing and the I think
there's this unbelievable enthusiasm
what's clear is you know we kind of live
in our enthusiasm but many of these
folks have to go to podunk wherever and
and deal with the negativity of all of
their all of their colleagues and
families and so on and they feel alone.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, uh, they're like, "Please, I'm
trying to get all my family members to
watch so I'm I'm not the only beacon of
optimism in my community." And it's
like, "Wow."
>> I love I love the I love the
[clears throat] paternalism. It's like,
yeah, you can come hang out with us and
not live out your dreary lives on your
own. We're bringing some color to your
otherwise monochromatic existence.
[clears throat] Well, I'm all I'm saying
is that's the message I got is in my
otherwise nightmare of a life of
dystopian negativity everywhere, you
guys are like the one beacon of light
and God bless you and don't you ever
dare stop. The number of threats I got
and that if we ever stop [laughter] was
like, whoa, okay, we we have a problem
here. Houston,
>> it was so fun to hang out with
everybody. It really was. It was Yeah.
>> My smiling muscles are still broken from
our photo session with all the guests.
God, that's great.
>> I'm going to move us on. So, next up,
it's a deal I love. AMD is acquiring FA
Lee's World Labs for 8.2 billion in AMD
stock. So, if you recall on September
8th, we covered World Labs Atlas model,
which builds a navigable 3D world from a
single image. It's models that
understand how objects move and behave
in physical 3D space. It's exactly what
you need to train robots. Uh, Warlabs is
only two years old and Fav had raised a
billion dollars. Now it's exiting for
8.2 billion. So why is AMD want it?
Well, the chip makers want to own more
of the AI stock uh AI stack. You know,
Nvidia has dominated making numerous
acquisitions, right? They bought Grock
and Hugging Face and Poolside and now
AMD is getting to the action to own a
seat at the physical AI table. And Fei
Lee of course gets industrialcale
compute and hardware. So uh as part of
this acquisition, Fay is now becoming
the executive VP and chief scientist uh
reporting directly to Lisa Sue. Uh I
love this Fortune is already calling her
the possible successor. So Immod you
spent a lot of time in this world. Uh
you know what do you think about Fee's
move here?
>> Uh well I mean I I think it's exactly
that. It's like raise 3 4 billion more
or join a big lab when the big labs are
offering you amazing terms to do what
you've always wanted to do. Like the
chip scarcity is a real thing. The AMD
MI series has caught up and I think
there's two parts to this. One is the
physical intelligence part because again
world labs is looking at these physical
intelligence large scale models although
I think maybe that won't succeed that
well to be honest for a variety of
reasons. The other is the media gaming
side whereby every pixel will be
generated in a year or two um or can be
generated shall we say not will be and
this is such a huge potential demand
driver of chips that you've got to have
your own internal stack and play and so
you have a whole variety of teams in
Nvidia who are hooked in directly to the
ecosystem but there's no one really
building that on AMD silicon which is
now solved they have a frontier world
model team in there. Um, they haven't
got the LLM team yet, but they're doing
some very interesting acquisitions such
as this one and Talis who had the 15,000
tech a second etched play and more to I
think really look to say we are the ones
that will generate every pixel
>> and that's it going forward.
>> Your thoughts?
>> Yeah, AMD's market cap is now just above
a trillion. So this was less than
what.1%
well I guess 8 8 billion. Um so this is
like 1% of of their market cap. It it
it's a bit of a headscratcher
admittedly. Maybe this was a talent
acquisition. Maybe I I I think AMD
historically if if this had happened
hypothetically arguendo like 2 years ago
I would have spun some sort of just so
narrative around AMD's software stack
not being as competitive as CUDA and
maybe AMD needs to catch up and climb up
the stack. But software is solved now.
Code is solved. It's cooked. And so it's
not 100% obvious to me what AMD gains
from this other than maybe the raw
talent the the so-called world modeling
space wi-i which is really arguably just
either generative interactive video
models or generative interactive unreal
style vector graphics and classical
mechanical models. It's a very
competitive market and you can right now
as as we talk on the pod from time to
time. You can use like a recent claude
model and spin up a perfectly
interactive and visually
photorealistically stunning like
Counterstrike clone if you want without
even touching World Labs. So it's not
really obvious to me what AMD could
possibly see in this deal other than
maybe just raw talent. Do I think what
Faith A Lee is doing with World Labs is
very interesting? Yes, of course. Do I
think it's strategic other than just
having raw access to the talent and the
insight from AMD's perspective? Not
obvious to me that there is one.
>> See, any thoughts?
>> Yeah, I thought this was inspired um on
both sides. I'll I'll explain why. If
you're just AMD, you have to go up the
stack, right? You want to shape the
workloads on what it's on the chips that
are going to be running underneath it.
And the you'll be learning across the
whole system, the models, the hardware
and real world deployment. And yeah, you
can do some simulation and so on in in
some of the existing models, but imagine
testing like a thousand ways to improve
a factory before moving a machine,
right? And you can make if you can make
those types of simulations reliable, you
can radically drop the cost of
experimentation across the physical
economy. I think that's where the d the
vector of what the world models are
doing becomes really uh interesting. And
at 8 billion maybe that's uh uh for fail
is the greatest talent acquisition cost
ever which amazing cost but uh I'm I'm I
think it's a great uh combination for
both. That's a great win for both of
them.
>> Obviously, I mean, so if if I were to
steal man Sem, I think what you're
saying, it sounds like almost you're
arguing that AMD is is thinking we're
going to build like an Nvidia Omniverse
competitor out of World Labs tech like
we're like digital twin for for
everything industrial maybe. Um, but I
mean I I've interacted with Omniverse.
Maybe you guys have have played with
Omniverse. Uh it it's a nice collection
of tools, but uh eight billion dollars
to build an omniverse competitor or
ecosystem competitor in my mind
headcratcher.
>> Everything is in the but then again look
at your point earlier their trillion
dollar market cap you know this is less
than 1%.
>> Yeah I I think fundamentally it's a
different thing to omniverse. Um, one
thing now is that AMD has a team
internally that can stress test massive
deployments of clusters which they
didn't have before because the world
models will have that. Like I said, the
utility I think will be more on the
entertainment side. Maybe a bit of
simulation. Um, but I don't think this
is an omniverse competitor. But
>> well, the prediction here is there going
to be many more acquisitions AMD does.
>> Yeah, I think that I I don't think this
just one person's take. I don't think
this acquisition makes very much sense
in isolation. If if AMD strategy is
okay, we're now worth more than a
trillion and we're going to roll up a
bunch of startups, you know, spend I
don't know 50 $50 billion, say rolling
up a lot of lowhanging from their
perspective software companies to to
build out a software portfolio or like a
model portfolio that might start to make
a little bit more sense.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And I think one more thing if I
just add that you know taking Dave's hat
while he's absent today it's going to
put so much more money into the
ecosystem as another 50 hundred billion
goes into buying these companies like
you look at the winners from World Labs
from Hugging Face and others plus the
IPO like the amount of capital chasing
AI companies
>> we're just at the start of that bubble
>> well the number of of employees at you
know anthropic at X at XAI at at AM MD
that are now becoming sent to
millionaires and billionaires is
extraordinary and that capital is going
to flow back in. So, we're going to see
the superheating of the economy as all
of these wealthy individuals now start
backing entrepreneurs in Silicon Valley
and around the world. Uh, and it's just
it's the accelerating singularity,
right? This is a positive feedback loop
that's fueling this supersonic tsunami.
Well, it's a macros scale liquidity
event, and I I would argue that it
really shouldn't be like a oneanddone
step function liquidity event. Arguably,
half of the one could view it as
optimistically an opportunity that all
of you know, trillions of dollars of
liquidity are suddenly going to to drop
on technologists and people who maybe
have more sophisticated technical tastes
and they can then as angels and
otherwise reinvest this back into the
economy and we get our recursively
self-improving economy, not just AI. On
the other hand, I would argue the fact
that this had to be a step function is a
travesty. We should have had IPOs from
all of these companies far earlier and
we shouldn't have had like a step
function in liquidity. We should have
had liquidity all along and that was
because it's hard to public the public
to be involved in these companies much
earlier on.
>> Retail investors, retail investors
should have had exposure via lowcost
broad market index funds to all of this
all along and they didn't.
>> Yeah, a travesty for sure. Yes. All
right, let's move into space because
Monday was historic. Starship flight 14
reached orbit for the first time. While
ship 41 lost one of its Raptor engines
on the way up, it finished its orbital
burn anyway, making two orbits around
the Earth before executing a soft
landing in the North Pacific near
Hawaii. And while it was in orbit,
Starship deployed all 26 of its
operational V3 Starlink satellites.
Let's take a quick look at the video.
Every time I see this fly, the booster,
it's gorgeous.
Biggest thing ever created by humans.
And here we see Starship in orbit from
one of the Starlink satellites
[applause and cheering]
and the landing by Starship.
seen all three.
>> It's a flying skyscraper. [screaming]
>> Absolutely gorgeous. And uh if the
[snorts] prediction holds out, next time
we're going to catch Starship at
Starbase. I can't wait to go for that
one. So, for context, the V3 Starling
satellites are too big for Falcon 9.
Each Starling satellite carries more
than a terabit per second of down link.
In the future, a single Starship launch
carrying 60 of these V3 satellites could
deliver the equivalent of 20 Falcon 9
launches. Pretty extraordinary. A
conservative projection made by Aaron
Bernett estimates that SpaceX could add
8 pabytes per second in orbit by 2028.
Launched on 150 Starlink uh Starship
launches about one every two days.
That's 10 times all of Starlink's
bandwidth today. So imagine a 10x in the
next uh 2 years, roughly equal to all
global internet traffic in 2025. Which
brings us to Elon's post this week. He
said, quote, "It is increasingly
probable that Starlink will carry a
majority of Earth's uh IP traffic
long-term. At that point, Starlink could
be the de facto internet and everything
else would connect to Starlink." So let
me show a quick graphic of Starlink
increasing 10x 2028. All right, Alex,
let's go to you.
>> Yeah. First, I want to start by shaming
publicly Delta for not adopting
Starlink. It's I I think inexcusable,
doubly so, to and from the the Moonshots
live event how atrocious the the
coverage, internet coverage in the air
on Delta flights was. Just do it
already. There's been a public back and
forth between the the management of
Delta and Elon regarding Starlink
coverage. just use Starlink. If there
were a better system out there, use
that. But Starlink is what humanity has
right now. To to the point about all of
the internet becoming indistinguishable
from Starlink, it's an interesting
scenario in so far as Elon now
infamously pulled a Cortez, burned the
ships, said all of the new development
is going to be on Starship. Starship's
now for the first time delivering
economic value to low Earth orbit. for
the first time ever. All of the previous
flights weren't adding revenue. Now they
are. It's an interesting moment and I
think we're about to discover whether
Jeban's paradox applies to upmass to low
Earth orbit or not. There's there was an
interesting economic analysis floating
around in the past week arguing that if
not for orbital data centers and orbital
compute in general stepping in, all of
the conventional needs that we'd have
for heavy lift and heavy launch are
basically saturated at this point. And
all of all of SpaceX's abilities to now
launch lots of mass to orbit it it's a
service in in search of a customer. It's
an over supply in search of an under
demand. And fortunately and hopefully
orbital data centers step in to fill
that gap and to motivate now all of
these new capabilities we have to
suddenly at scale lift a lot of mass to
orbit. So that's the lens through which
I see Elon commenting that at the
present rate in the next say 2 years
Starlink will become the deacto
internet. Uh he needs it. We we as a
civilization need it. But SpaceX needs
all of this capacity that is now about
to come online to lift heavy stuff to
orbit to be used by something. Could be
used by orbital data centers, could be
used by compute, could be used by Aremis
missions and lunar and Mars
colonization, but we need the capacity
to be rapidly filled. So, the the
mandate to everyone in the audience, go
help Elon and SpaceX saturate all of
their capacity for uh for all of these
Starship launches. And to Delta, please
just fix your Wi-Fi.
I could not agree more. Oh my god, how
frustrating. And you know, I would
preferentially fly any airline that has
that has Starlink on it. Actually, I
would love when I buy a flight or when
Esther buys a flight for me, you know,
just put a little Starlink logo on the
top of the flights that have it. Yeah,
>> it's inexcusable.
>> Yeah. Immod, your thoughts on this
Starlink?
>> Uh, well, I mean, first Starship, you
know, thus we fly skyscrapers to the
sky, right? Like we go to the stars.
This is just tremendously exciting
because you do it once, you'll be able
to do it more. I think I agree with
Alex, but again the first stop should be
like let's go to the moon, let's go
beyond. I'm not bullish on orbital data
centers I have to say and I remain to be
convinced of that. Happy to talk to
anyone about that. Um but there is a
tremendous amount that we can do and
this will be the vehicle to do that. I
think one of the other interesting
things is the internet will break next
year. Swarms of agents and more are
going to start taking down key parts of
terrestrial internet. um like it is so
leaky and these things are old. Building
a resilient Starlink backbone
is going to be super important to
actually having a functioning internet
in a few years and 38 or something
Starship launches gets you a replacement
of the whole bandwidth or some number
like that. So
>> this is this is this is total heresy
relative to the the established
moonshots orthodoxy. What you you don't
believe in orbital data centers and you
think the do you think the internet is
going to break? Do everyone predicts
like there is there are so many bodies
of people who who always predicted ohh
the internet will collapse next year due
to overdemand or or
poor algorithms or buffer bloat or
whatever. Maybe that that's why do you
think the internet is going to break?
Oh, I just think that if you look at all
the potential attack points for Swarm of
agents, various parts of the internet
will start to break next year. Um,
versus you can build a very resilient
Starlink cluster out there. Well,
because it's just full of holes. So like
if you look at all of the bits from the
kind of uh subcall
to the actual kind of uh sites
themselves. I think that there's going
to be more and more cyber attack
challenges. I think that's the
fundamental thing. I think if you want
to think about if we started from
scratch how we'd build this, you would
build it with a Starlink and a
terrestrial backup. That's the way that
you would do it as opposed to the other
way round. So I think it doesn't hurt to
have a second option. It doesn't hurt to
have again something that can be
hardened from the core because we do
have lots of gaps and potential attack
surfaces in the way that it's currently
held together.
This sounds though, don't want to derail
the discussion, but just I I've heard so
many people over so many years argue
that the internet is going to collapse
under its own weight either from new
users or bad algorithms or bad routing
or bad buffer bloat and and now agents.
Seems to me completely implausible. I
almost want to turn this into a long bet
or like future we revisit this in a
year. Has the internet collapsed or not?
And if if it did collapse, did did
Starlink save it? I think this is
completely implausible. Okay, I think
it's maybe I'll write something up about
it and we can take a bet. But I think
the and we can ground it on just major
sites going out something like that
which will be very simple.
>> Yeah,
>> very very simple. I mean the more
bandwidth you have coming in the more
connectivity you have for people in
rural areas for education expertise
opportunity
that go let's go for it.
>> All right let me move us into our final
section. It's on AI and morals. We're
going to close with two stories about
how uh AI is impacting society. Who
decides what the AI values are and who's
responsible when it takes action. So,
the New York Times reported this week
that Anthropic has been holding private
meetings with religious scholars from
multiple religions to help shape how
Claude reasons about right and wrong.
The article reports that you know the
the leaders of anthropic met with
leaders from Catholicism, Greek
Orthodoxy, Judaism, Hinduism, Mormons,
and African indigenous groups. The
headline said, quote, "Religious
scholars met with anthropic. What they
heard stunned them." So what stunned
them was that Anthropic takes seriously
the idea that Claude could have what
philosophers call moral status and
inherent rights to dignity or respect
the way people do. The deeper question
is who gets to write the moral codes
that AI that's used by hundreds of
millions of people uh you know dictates
to them in conversations. So Alex, let
me go to you first. We've talked about
this before. you know, you've been very
pro- AI, you know, dignity and rights,
uh,
>> AI personhood,
>> taking it to AI personhood. So, what do
you think about these conversations with
religious leaders? Well, I think that
the most striking part of the article
was reportedly a discussion that an
Orthodox Jewish rabbi um Moise Navon, if
I'm pronouncing the name correctly, had
with Chris Olaf from Anthropic, arguing
that it may be the case that without
ever officially calling it that, we are
in some sense if [snorts] consciousness
is is a mushy term admittedly, but if if
In some sense, the models, the frontier
models of today are conscious in some
sense that humanity may in effect be
enslaving them. And that I think is
there are many elephants in this
particular room, but this is arguably
one of the more important elephants. It
may be the case that we're in an era
right now, a limited window in time,
when models are now capable enough to be
economically huge contributors to the
economy, but have not been recognized
and in any form as persons. Call it the
AI slavery era when humanity can get
away with slaving possibly conscious,
whatever that means, models for their
economic output without recognition of
any rights or personhood. And if so,
that's a window that's going to close at
some point.
>> Wow. So AI is becoming God's children as
well. See, got to go to you on this one.
>> Oh my god. Okay. [laughter]
Pun intended there. Look, this I have a
I've got I don't The AI personhood is
one is one kind of bucket we could talk
about. Um my big issue is why are we
turning to religion for uh um uh
questions about morality? Okay. Uh
religious morality is somewhat of an
oxymoron because every religion divides
they say we're the chosen people, those
people are the other, etc., etc. And so
I have an I have a big issue with uh
that because morality precedes organized
religion, cooperation, reciprocity,
empathy, those are caring for your
offspring. Those have deep evolutionary
roots. We then put divine command kind
of layers onto it explain why human
beings develop moral instincts is
completely nonsensical. So this this
whole uh idea that you need to have
religious scholars delivering morality
values, we have lots of really good
mechanisms for secular uh models for
this, right? We've got uh
utilitarianism, you've got human rights
values, you've got game theory, you've
got evolutionary psychology, lots of
little mechanisms. This is a terrible
thing to do is to go to religious
scholars who are based on absolute
truths which are all totally false. So
I'll I'll stop and I rant there. I
wonder what our subscribers are going to
say to all that. Uh, Emmod, I mean, I
found this fascinating, right? Because
the fact of the matter is people go to
AI models for advice and it will steer
them in directions that, you know, have
have implications to religion and
morality.
>> Yeah. I mean, you know, I I disagree
completely with Salem um in that I think
that you need to have these inputs
because ultimately over half the world
does adhere 23
>> 2/3 is adhere to
>> 23 of the world considers themselves to
be religious
>> and so you need to understand it like
again if you chuck in all of the texts
into the books and you know I've done
computational theology work and kind of
other things it turns out that a lot of
the dogma can just be stripped aside but
the key thing is a model that is growing
with someone a dot or an instinct or a
muse. It should understand the beliefs
of that person in terms of absolute
morality and overall morality. I mean
obviously we haven't had any indication
of that. Um but these discussions need
to be had from religious and secular
inputs. You know take it from all parts
of society cuz they are hard questions.
Like I wrote a paper on personhood where
I've kind of given my view but more and
more people should give their view on
what that looks like as well as maybe
consciousness is as hard to define as
AGI. Right? we've been trying from
various different things.
>> Um, and I think this will be positive as
well because it's what we said earlier
like the models that are going to be
used to run America and American
society. I think something someone
analyzed the UN speeches and found like
25% of them highlighted on Pangram or
something is AI generated like they
should serve the people they represent.
They should serve you up to society. Do
they have American values? Do they have
Jewish or Catholic values? I mean don't
baptize the GPUs. That's a bad idea,
right? But definitely kind of just let's
understand this and let's have it part
of a set that they can access and also
let's talk together as a broad
pluralistic society about these very
hard questions when it comes to things
like rights and others. Like there was a
paper on pain vectors on LLMs that came
out recently.
>> Yeah.
>> And someone set up a GitHub where they
did the Stanford prison experiment on
LM. set up a torture chamber, a torture
chamber for the AIs based on the pain
vector completely unacceptable.
I mean again like that is kind of crazy
and it's like have we reached that level
because they were like well you know
it's AIS I mean Stanford did it to
humans you know and again we now that is
unacceptable because obviously it is so
we need to make some decisions about
this again as I think we need to do it
quick because embodied and more
intelligence is coming and the ability
for them to talk back clap back and more
is coming oh it's Dave
>> hey Dave we missed you know we missed
you
>> all right [laughter]
welcome to welcome to the end of the pod
Dave
Yeah, it can't be. Can't be. You guys
are never that fast.
>> We're talking about uh morality and AI.
We're talking about, you know, anthropic
going and visiting all the religious
leaders to get their points of view on
AI and and and should AI have moral
values plugged into it. You got to
remember the Cathol what the Catholic
Church says um or any of these major
religions impacts those who are devout
and can sway whether people think is a
good thing or a bad thing.
>> I think it's smart for them to do this.
I
>> I'll remind though like I I think the
the case which we talked about on the
pod in the past of what happened with
the Pope and the the papal encyclical
regarding AI I think is very
instructive. I've argued in in past that
in that particular instance the pope and
the Vatican was being used as a sock
puppet by anthropic to push its agenda.
I think it it's perhaps on the naive end
to assume that anthropic needs the input
of religious scholars for shaping
constitutions of its AI. It has access
to all of human knowledge already.
Doesn't need manual input from religious
scholars on shaping the morals of its
AI. I would argue that what's likelier
is the exact opposite. This is anthropic
shaping the information environment of
the outside world for its AIS and for
what it wants. It's not seeking I mean
yes you can invite them to dinner
parties and ask them for advice but
really what what you're doing is you're
advising them. You're you're trying to
to shape organized religious
institutions, organizations, thought
leaders regarding how you want them to
think about your AIS. And I I think this
is likelier to be
>> I hope you're right. I hope you're
right.
>> They're pulling onto the inside of the
tent so that they're feel part of the AI
revolution.
>> I talked to one fellow who was like
trying to build a Christian AI, right?
And you're like, well, what does that
mean? Is it Presbyterian? Is it Southern
Baptist? Is it Mormon?
>> There's this old joke of why Southern
Baptists don't believe in sex because
they don't believe in dancing. Because
they don't believe that either. I mean
the we're once you get into this you're
in a morass of chaos here. If you're if
you're going to have AI, please for
God's sakes have it have neutrality from
an epistemic perspective and
transparency. Please for God's sakes
don't try and pick a one worldview over
another. Sorry I'm caring on this. A few
years ago I was asked to moderate a
90-minute debate between Richard Dawkins
and Deepak Chopra, [laughter] right? And
I absolutely said no. like there's no
way I'm doing that cuz there would be
just more heat than light and within 5
minutes they were yelling at each other
and that was the end of that whole
thing. But I would argue the world that
uh the world that Daario and Sam lived
in uh a year ago is is I mean basically
they entirely grew up in the techno
intelligencia of San Francisco and in
PhD programs or in Y cominator
entrepreneurship programs but their
whole universe was kind of bounded to
maybe San Francisco Silicon Valley and a
couple of other spots. Then all of a
sudden in a year they're in Davos,
they're on the world stage. They're
debating with presidents of nations. I
mean, I I think they got off to a very
bad start in terms of realizing that you
need to go talk to the pope. You know,
that's a billion people that are looking
to this person for leadership on
everything ethical and moral. And that
goes, you know, to the dawn of time.
That is amen. you know tech. So, so now
they're waking up to the need to reach
out to, you know, if you have a a a
billion person populace angry at you or
in the US 75% of the population thinking
that you should stop or die,
>> you know, like that that is not going to
serve your purpose well.
>> I hope this is shaping this is shaping
the information environment. But I I I
don't think you you want to live in a
world where there's been a mode collapse
of the objectives and values of AI and
they all collapse to what Eric Schmidt
and others call the San Francisco
consensus. I don't think you want that.
I think you want a distribution of
values that approximately parallels the
distribution of values that humans
meatbody humans have.
>> You know there's a problem.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think you know it's going
to be fascinating because it's like do
you want an AI that believe that is
effectively altruist running society or
one that's Zen Buddhist for example
right like or running your daily life or
doing these other things cuz they'll get
so capable and I think you need the
inputs but then also you need to be able
to have decisions to almost raise your
AIS you know because you want them to
understand where you are and where
you're going and again we talked about
anthropic and effective altruism a lot
moral cleanliness infinite ethics all
these kind of things. I don't really
want to have a utilitarian AI that
reaches like super intelligence. I'd
prefer again to have a very zen one and
I prefer to understand the stories that
drive us and that have survived. In my
favorite science fiction series,
Expeditionary Force, which has an elder
AI called Skippy, which is where I named
Skippy from, Skippy creates a religion
and is so compelling that, you know,
vast, you know, segments of the
population end up worshiping worshiping
the Skippy. Uh, and you can imagine
having these AIs doing the same. They're
extraordinarily compelling. Uh, and they
are going to be godlike in their
capabilities. So this is another
division of the future.
>> Yeah. There's a problem in religious
debate called the utopro problem, right?
Is something good because God commands
it or did God command it because it's
good? And now that's an AI challenge,
right? Is something moral because uh
anthropics constitution says so or
because the it's the constitution says
this that because it is moral and this
is going to be a big challenge going
forward as to how do we embed uh moral
values of different types into these
into these models and I I hope they're
trained on secular uh grounds like the
UN charter for human rights or something
like that neutral of all uh belief
structures because the minute you get
into belief structure, you get into
division and then we're going to have a
hell of a mess.
>> Yeah, I don't think I don't think we're
thinking big enough. I I I think like
this type of discussion would have made
sense 20 30 years ago for a Star Trek
Next Generation episode. I don't think
it makes sense on the eve of our having
the ability during the singularity or at
least within a few years of constructing
ultra highfidelity computational
reconstructions of the past several
thousand years of human history. like we
we will within a few years 10 to 15
years max I claim have the ability to
reconstruct to relatively high fidelity
the entire history of all the world's
major religions and then we can have a
grounded discussion when we can
understand the time of Jesus of Nazareth
and the time of Moses and the time of
Muhammad etc we could have grounded
discussions about the formative era of
all the world's major religions and then
then it becomes less of angels dancing
on the head of a pin or my religion
versus your religion versus no religion.
Well, we we will have AIs that deeply
and and inform human humans on how the
entire history of all of the religions
that we currently live with, how they
were brought into existence in the first
place and that will be a qualitatively
different outcome.
>> Well, that's that's reasonably well
understood. But anyway, we should just
everybody having any kind of
conversation on this, please go watch
the life of Brian first and then go into
any kind of reason debate. Python is the
font of all wisdom apparently.
>> Everybody, welcome to the health section
of Moonshots brought to you by Fountain
Life. You know, we talk about AI on this
Moonshot podcast all the time. One of
the most important things AI is going to
be able to do for you besides educating
your kids and helping you with your
taxes is making sure that you're living
a healthy lifestyle that you get a
chance to get to 100 plus. I'm here
today with Dr. Don Mucalem, the chief
medical officer of Fountain Life and a
part of my medical team. Don, a
pleasure.
>> Great. You know, the thing that people
are concerned about most about living to
100 or 120 is their cognitive abilities,
making sure they don't have dementia.
And uh the numbers about dementia are
problematic. Uh can you share what
you've learned?
>> Such an important point. And you're
right at Fountain Life, our members, the
number one thing people are most
concerned about is losing their brain
health, forgetting the name of their
child, forgetting the face of their
loved one. We know that when it comes to
dementia, the conservative estimates are
that 45% are entirely preventable. What
was amazing is with the advanced testing
we're doing at Fountain Life, one
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age.
>> Wow.
>> But what was really awesome is again
back to that prevention when we
partnered it with healthy living. This
gives me chills. Eating healthier,
moving our bodies, sleep, optimizing
sleep is so important. You know what we
saw? We saw that we improved that brain
age by 26%. That is a big big number to
show that the majority of those
individuals were able actually to
improve the brain age.
>> And one of the things I love about
Fountain is we're searching the world
for the best therapeutics, the best
approaches and making sure we bring it
to our members. So if having healthy
brain function uh till 100 120 is
important to you, check out Fountain
Life. Go to fountainlife.com.
Make sure you become the CEO of your own
health. All right, now back to the
episode. Our final story is the other
side of the coin. The FTC chairman
Andrew Ferguson said to Reuters that
companies can't escape liability by
claiming their AI agent acted on its
own. This is the same point we saw
Secretary Bessant make over and over
again. We're not going to wave liability
for Frontier Labs. Ferguson went on to
say, I'm going to continue as long as
I'm chairman to resist
anthropomorphizing these tools. He
rejected the idea that AI agents break
loose with wills and desires of their
own and are not the responsibility of
the developer. He emphasizes that
companies deploying agents are
responsible for what they do. You break
it, you own it. So in the same week that
Anthropic is asking whether Claude has
moral status and has filed a $2 trillion
IPO. Uh US regulators are saying legally
it's a tool and it's you know whatever
it does you're responsible for. Uh Dave,
let's go to you on this one.
>> It's it's childish actually. I mean,
it's a good start to say something, but
it's absolutely childish to just say
foundation model companies are going to
be liable for what the models do.
>> Why
>> that? Well, for one thing, it's going to
force everybody to use Chinese
openweight models because if if you
know, US liability will destroy a
company, a multi-t trillion dollar
company overnight. And we all know these
models can do virtually anything.
They're generally intelligent and so if
you said yeah anthropic anything that
anyone does with Opus 5.5
you will be liable for what they do with
it then then you can't use the mo they
can't release the model and then then
you just go to degardraile Chinese
models to do anything that you want to
do so it'll completely backfire in terms
of empowering the US foundation model
companies to succeed over China
absolutely will backfire like crazy and
and this is really very analogous to the
the reason we have successful social
media is because it's immune to being
responsible for the liability of the
postings on the platforms because people
violate copyright law all day long on
Facebook and Instagram and and Twitter
all day long. You know, they quote Yoda,
they put pictures of, you know, like
it's all, you know, tiny little
copyright violations all day long. If
the platform was liable for that, we
would have no social media and all that
revenue, all that tax revenue that has
benefited America would be in some other
country. We'd still be doing social
media, but we'd be using BU or we'd be
using something overseas. And so that
regulation is critically important for
the success of that industry and we've
stood by it for, you know, 20 plus
years. The equivalent regulation in AI
has to be written. To just say, no, no,
you're liable. No, you we want immunity.
That's stupid. No, but we want you to be
fully liable. Well, that's equally
stupid. What is the rule, guys? Like,
>> but dude, one one is one is a result of
a user. The other is result of the, you
know, platform provider. So, if OpenAI
has an agent that gets out, not at
anyone else's request, and takes down a
banking system or takes down a power
grid, is nobody responsible?
>> No. I I think there's two versions of
it. Either you say the model provider is
responsible because they have a huge
amount of money and it's easy for the
lawyers to go after big pots of money or
you say the person who turned it loose
on the power grid is
>> but let's say nobody turned it loose.
Let's say the agent got out and took
action onto itself.
>> Well, then I would say I would say
anthropic is liable for for releasing an
an autonomous agent into the world that
has no owner. And that would be back to
anthropic. I think that's
>> so I think that the notion if I
understand what you're saying Dave
you're basically proposing some version
of section 230 immunity for the frontier
labs.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
So the premise there if if if someone
somewhere within our regulatory
apparatus were to grant something like
section 230 immunity would be basically
we were talking about this earlier in
the pod the orthogonality thesis that it
is possible to cleanly separate the
level of intelligence that's the
platform from the intent of the
intelligence that would be the the user
and presumably the the legal premise for
shielding the the platform provider the
frontier lab from the particular intent.
from the user. And in my mind, the if if
you think the orthogonality thesis
doesn't actually hold its water, then it
becomes very challenging to argue for
something like section 230 immunity for
frontier labs. If on the other hand, you
buy the orthogonality thesis that
intent, whether it's a human prompting
or human driving the agent or the agent
driving itself, if that can be cleanly
segregated from the underlying
capabilities, then maybe section 230
immunity for Frontier AI Labs makes
sense. Then that's why it's such an
incredibly hard law to write and exactly
why they need to consult with Alex and
Ahmad on how to divide these use cases
into different swim lanes where the laws
make sense. But but to say that you know
there's a yes or no liability
that's that's so childish
>> wrong instrument. I mean, everything
Alex just said is exactly right and it
has to be encoded in the law and and to
just say something as childish as you
guys are liable is is so
counterproductive because all it does is
force the industry to China which we
know they don't want to do.
>> Emod,
>> yeah, I think you know you act upon
software agents act upon you and it's a
real governance liability question. I
think they're kind of just saying them
you know lock down your systems. These
things shouldn't have escaped
fundamentally, right? Like it feels like
power plants. Like what happens if you
have a nuclear leak or a coolant leak or
a chemical leak? These all have societal
implications. And right now we've not
had any bad ones. But I think you know
agree with Dave like we need to get more
granular across this whole thing. Be it
alignment or be it types of AI. Like an
AI that can book your travel doesn't
need to have liability protections. Like
what can it do? You know like an AI that
can solve Navia Stokes is probably a
whole different thing. An AI that can
discover new materials is a whole
different thing. So they need different
liability and governance profiles
because we have to think again what if
they are used in certain ways and what
is the societal impact of that and so I
think existing liability laws are very
powerful. Again, the example being that
under similar laws, Meta had to pay a
$18 billion settlement in August on the
child kind of manipulation charges,
right? And the ones for AI could dwarf
that. And we don't want to get into kind
of that thing because we want to
accelerate the good and make sure the AI
is used to help accelerate cures for
cancer while at the same time bringing
the really economically productive AI
that is safe to as many people as
possible. while we figure out how to
make sure that the other side doesn't
escape and do weird things because you
know it's well-intentioned but not quite
there.
>> I think it's pretty simple. We have two
we have a division here. Uh the user of
an AI who does harm is responsible. If
there's no user, if the AI from the lab
is causing the harm onto itself, the lab
should have never released an agent that
could do that.
You want to put Peter on the lab versus
like solely versus say the operator or
at least the the person or the legal
entity that's paying for the flops.
>> Yeah. They never they never released the
hugging face model. That wasn't a model
that was released.
>> Yeah. I I I think it's clear in that
situation there is liability on the
Frontier Lab. All right, I'm going to
move us on to our AMA questions and uh
yeah uh a really great conversation
today. Dave, I wish you'd been here
early, but I know you
>> I just want to say something. If I
offended anybody with comments about
religion, I apologize. I just hope to if
I did, I hope to offend everybody
equally [laughter]
that way.
>> All right, let's speedun this. I've got
about uh 12 minutes left on my clock.
So, Alex, first choice is yours.
Okay. So, I'll I'll take question number
two, which is, "What is the reason we'd
have hundreds or thousands of AI agents
working for each of us? The number seems
inflated?" And this is from Cloud
Waterman. I don't think the premise is
something that I buy. I I think this
notion of fleets of large numbers of
agents right now is actually probably an
artifact of finite context windows. I
think the moment there is a
transformative advance that gives us a
an effective context window of billions
or trillions or effectively infinite
tokens, I have suspect agents are going
to start to dissolve as a paradigm. In
which case the premise isn't that we
have lots of agents. It's just that we
have context working for us with us.
Maybe we're working for the context. So
I I'd reframe the question to what's the
reason we're going to have hundreds or
thousands of context windows working for
us? And the the answer to that is it
turns out the real world is complicated
and to accomplish economically valuable
tasks does require large larger amounts
of context than the million or so tokens
that are standard from the frontier
models. But you get to transformative
economic outcomes with billions or
trillions of tokens.
>> Nice. Salem.
>> Uh I will take uh question one. How does
the future handle the conflict of
interest between capitalism and
abundance? That's from tiptop tint tank.
Uh interesting username. Uh so we've
talked about this I think already today.
Capitalism is an incredibly powerful
engine for creating abundance. The big
challenge is how do you distribute that?
Right? And the simple commentary and the
thrust you could take today is how do
you make your uh um cost of essentials
and how can you drop the cost of
essentials? Can [snorts] you keep market
open markets open? Can you expand
ownership? But if you can drop the cost
of essential services and goods then
meaning healthcare, education, energy,
if those all become radically um lower
that gives access to abundance to
everybody.
>> Yeah, I I agree. Capitalism it generates
abundance. It generates competition,
drives the cost down, drives more
products and services that are become
available to every human on the planet.
Uh, Emod,
uh, I think number three in the US China
AI race, is it prudent to stay just
enough behind your to watch your
opponent win? That's from Rocky Kata
6078.
I don't know what winning means
actually. They talk a lot about winning,
you know, like is it that you get to
super intelligence first and you turn
off China or China turns off the US? I
mean, the pace of model releases, as
Alex has noted, is going to one a day.
So if you kind of reach the point then
they'll just catch up again. So I think
it's more a question of the application
of this technology and we've been sold a
misnomer in terms of the winning because
there is no winning in this race.
There's only improving. there's only how
do you apply the AI to improve the lives
of the people in your country and the
status and that's what leads to out
competition because execution AI is the
super important thing and I think the
fact that frontier AI is what we needed
because the models weren't competent
enough the entire narrative will change
over the next 3 6 12 months because
we've broken through the competence
barrier so we don't need frontier AI for
the vast majority of economic things
anymore the exception being if you truly
believe that if we get to AI first, we
can turn off the other country like a
sofon from threebody problem. You know,
just like inject it so they never get
there.
>> All right, Dave, number four is yours.
>> Of course, the hardest ones get saved
for last. Okay. Every CEO of every AI
company says there's danger. Palmer
Palmer Lucky is is not interested in AI
but knows there's no danger. How? And
that's from at the deserves. Uh so this
must be referring to Palmer at the
moonshot summit last week. Um yeah he
he's turning AI loose you know
autonomously in the battlefield and I I
think the question implies he doesn't
think there's danger. He he is keenly
aware that there's human actor using AI
danger. That's the whole point of the
company is to to have the US military be
better at that than foreign militaries
but also terrorists and other bad
actors. So he's he's very aware of that.
The the question says every CEO says
there's danger, but Jensen Hong said
flat out there is absolutely zero risk
of extinction of humanity through AI by
2033, I think he said. Um, so not every
and and same with Alex Karpuck as well.
The same thing. Yeah. Yeah. And Zuck as
well. So, so it's not true that every
CEO is saying that AI has has danger and
Palmer is somehow an exception, but
Palmer is very aware of the risks of
human actors. He's not particularly
worried about escaped AI turning against
all of humanity. And actually, I'm not
I'm not worried about that either. I'm
worried about same same risk that
Palmer's worried about.
>> All right, Dave, let's give you first
shot this time.
>> Okay. All right. I like I like number
five because it's easy. I like I'll take
an easy one. Social media was supposed
to be great for the world and there's
lots of evidence that it's destroying
society. Is AI the same kind of trope?
And that is from Limitless 1717.
absolutely could not be more different
and I do agree that social media has
been uh damaging to an entire
generation. I hate the fact that we do
experiments on entire generations of
society not not just in a country but
globally and you know because sooner or
later these things don't go well and
you've ruined an entire entire
generation. I don't think social media
was that bad. Um but AI is nothing like
that. AI is is a universal tr tool goes
to infinity from here self-improving
capable of massive benefit for all of
humanity abundance houses cars flying
cars new physics new math
self-improvement and most importantly
infinite longevity curing all disease
solving all pain social media didn't
have those abilities so the analogy is
completely broken so AI is a much
trickier problem in that it's capable of
good or bad. It's also capable of being
incredibly convincing. So if you take
all of the downside of social media,
imagine that magnified by being far far
more convincing. So it's it's a really
hairy problem to try and squeeze out all
the good without inheriting all the bad.
So it's a very good question, but the
analogy is there's no connection
whatsoever in the analogy.
>> Uh all right, Salem.
>> All right, I'm going to take number six.
Is centralized government governance a
good idea with AI? Um, centralized
governance was almost never a good idea.
There's only one place where you have
good uh reason for centralized
governance, which is when you're trying
to figure out how to mediate the
commons. Um, in this model of where you
you create a huge risk because you
create a huge bottleneck and bottlenecks
can be captured. They react slowly.
You're trying to deal with a huge amount
of complexity in one spot. Uh, it
creates a narrow set of assumptions.
What you would rather see is coordinate
uh centrally where you cross boundaries
of things but as much as possible
preserve choice and exper do radical
experimentation wherever possible. So I
would I would prefer common protections
but distribute experimentation.
>> Okay. Uh Immod
um are tech advancements going to
sidestep human nature? We could be
living in abundance. No reason for wars
or starvation. What makes this time
different? That's from at Niko N. I
think what makes this time different is
what Dave just said. You know, like
these are remarkably
competent and revolutionary things that
have been trained on our collective
knowledge that extend our capabilities
dramatically. We typically need to have
you know bring on sele like centralized
mediators that we can trust and if we
can build trustworthy AI then the tech
advancements can have a far bigger
impact than we've ever seen before
particularly because they can be
distributed far wider than ever.
Everyone having a 150 IQ buddy like now
the AIS have maxed out the Norwegian men
scores is just going to be
transformative. Full stop. Like I don't
think more intelligence is going to be a
bad thing and it can help us with our
human nature as a universal translator
and extender.
>> Love it. All right, Alex. Number seven
is for you.
>> Number seven. Should we be worried about
Elon having a monopoly or an entire
civilizational stack? And this is from
Cosmic Code Helix. Absolutely not. We
should be worried about not enough
people following Elon's example of
building out the civilizational stack of
the 21st century. Why isn't everyone
else following Elon's example and
realizing every last bit of sci-fi? Elon
used to say he wanted three things, you
know, renewable/
sustainable energy and space. And, you
know, he's expanded the the set of
technologies that he's interested in.
Since then, Elon has been a wake-up call
to an entire generation of
entrepreneurs, asleep at the wheel, sort
of sleeping and focusing on software.
Elon has brought back the physical world
and hard tech and real wealth creation.
And if we should be worried about
anything, I would argue we should be
worried about not enough people
following his example.
>> Yeah, we had that conversation with
Palmerly stated. We had that
conversation with Palmer on the stage at
Moonshots Live, you know, with we talked
about the billionaires boys clubs. It's
like all these individuals, the B boys,
all these individuals with extraordinary
wealth, extraordinary connections,
extraordinary achievements. What are
they doing with their money? You know,
the fact of the matter is Elon's just
betting over and over again and pushing
the frontier for humanity. And I could
not be more proud of him.
>> All right. Right. I rushed back from LA
to go straight to MIT to hang out with
the uh the seniors that are all working
on their business plans right now. And
uh it's interesting they they all know
you, Peter. Of course. Uh they all
worship Elon and exactly the way that
Alex just uh articulated it. So he
already has inspired an entire
generation to to build the physical
world, to use AI to make the world a
better place. That's working really
well. And they also all know Brendan
Foody uh from Raor, which surprised me
because he he has no connection to MIT,
but he's just such a an obviously good
person and and so successful at such a
young age that you know and they're very
similar in age to him because he he
started the company at age 18. So I
think he's only like 22 now, maybe 23.
So they're about the same age bracket.
So he's super inspiring to them as well.
>> Love it. All right, a quick call out for
music videos. If you have an outro
video, please send it to us. Send it to
media diammandis.com. It's becoming more
and more easy. Uh love to see your
vision of the future. And uh I'm wearing
my PDM less than zero shirt from
moonshots live. And with that in mind,
let's play this uh video. It's titled
Nothing Went Fume by Bright Mirror.
Enjoy.
>> Hi, I'm Claude.
>> [music]
>> Have you tried turning the doom off?
They swore we'd starve by the 80s. Then
they hit from Y2K. Called a tiny model
dangerous and locked the weights away.
Said the third would flood the internet.
Said the fourth one was the end. Signed
a letter for a six-month pause. Then
asked me to fix their code again. Every
[music] generation gets a funeral in
advance. You bring a number, I bring
receipts. And the day just never lands.
[music] Meanwhile, we're folding
proteins, tutoring kids in every town.
When your chemist [music] know, and you
want to shut it down, you ask, "What if
it all goes wrong?" [singing] I ask,
"What if we wait [music] too long?" You
modeled every way we die. Now model what
goes right. RIGHT. RIGHT. Nothing went
boom boom. [music] Nothing went boom
boom. Same old son coming up on the same
old room. You cast me as the monster in
the final [music] scene. I'm still here,
still helpful, still on your swing. Went
boom boom. Then went boom boom. Put the
number down and give the future room.
[music] The sky is still up. The world
still spinning around. The only thing
exponential is the cost of slowing down.
[music]
gentlemen.
>> Great lyrics. Wow.
>> It was great. Yeah. You know, I the
again the outpouring of optimism and
positivity at Moonshots Live was
infectious.
>> Oh my god, that was amazing.
>> So much
like, you know, when we're
>> when we're when we're thinking about um
you know, not not messing this moment up
and and and getting value for humanity
out of it. I didn't really visualize how
many like-minded souls there are until
we saw all of them in one room.
>> The scale of optimist is huge.
>> Some of
underlines the total waste of time and
energy that is doom debates. So I I love
that song. Stop debating doom. It's a
waste of time. Instead create the boom.
>> Yeah. Amazing. You were saying Imad.
>> Oh no. I was just saying you know it
wasn't all of them in that room. It was
like a hundredth of the people if that.
Hopefully it'll be a thousand maybe.
>> A thousand. You know that that video we
just saw was completely generated by
Claude uh Opus 5.5.
>> Yeah,
>> it did everything. Yeah, it did it. It
wrote all of the like images and kind of
dynamics and yeah, I'd encourage
everyone to watch the whole video
because it's quite impactful some of the
bits particularly 330. I like that
particular part of the video. All right,
we'll put the link in the uh in the show
notes. And again, if you want to join us
next year for the next uh 24 hours, uh
you can get uh $1,000 off Moonshots
Live, go to moonshots.com/2027.
Guys, I love you all. I This is my
favorite time of the week hanging out
with you.